<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religio bibliopolæ in imitation of Dr. Browns Religio medici, with a supplement to it / by Benj. iBrgwater [sic], Gent.</title>
            <author>Dunton, John, 1659-1733.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19049</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12877137</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12877137</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94860</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29388)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94860)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 731:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religio bibliopolæ in imitation of Dr. Browns Religio medici, with a supplement to it / by Benj. iBrgwater [sic], Gent.</title>
                  <author>Dunton, John, 1659-1733.</author>
                  <author>Bridgewater, Benjamin.</author>
                  <author>Browne, Thomas, Sir, 1605-1682. Religio medici.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for P. Smart ..., and are to be sold at the Raven ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Dunton as part of a larger uncompleted work; Dunton here published this part under the name of Bridgewater who assisted him in the writing. cf. NUC pre-1956 v. 151, p. 224.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian ethics.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94860:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94860:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Religio Bibliopolae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Imitation of Dr. Browns RELIGIO MEDICI.</p>
            <p>WITH A SUPPLEMENT to it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Benj. iBrgwater,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>P. Smart,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Raven</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94860:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94860:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Author</hi> of this Treatiſe not having leiſure to finiſh this Piece as he intended, being call'd aſide upon unavoidable Reaſons, we have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd to ſupply that Defect by another Hand, yet with all the care poſſibly to reach the <hi>Air,</hi> and <hi>Stile</hi> of the <hi>Author,</hi> which is of that neatneſs and facility as muſt needs recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it (were there nothing elſe conſiderable) to the taſte of ſuch an <hi>Age</hi> as this. The <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> being obvious and eaſy, the <hi>Notions</hi> bold and intelligible, aad the <hi>Whole</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out acted with ſuch a <hi>Spirit</hi> of Life and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, as certainly can never fail of accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the truly Learned and Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94860:3"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ſuch Prejudices do we labour, and our conceptions of Things are for the moſt part ſo irregular and monſtrous, that but to attempt our Delivery, and ſet us free from the ſlaviſh Power of <hi>Cuſtom</hi> and <hi>Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> wherewith we are ſo miſerably involv'd, merits no ſmall <hi>Commendation,</hi> tho the Succeſs be unanſwerable to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking: But to clear our <hi>dim ſight,</hi> to take the Film from our Eyes, and place us in the open <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine</hi> of Reaſon, and true Judgment; to acquaint us with the <hi>prerogative</hi> of our own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, and the due liberty and freedom of uſing them, is an <hi>Atchievement</hi> that exacts the higheſt Applauſe and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude from the better and nobler part of Mankind.</p>
            <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reby we are enabled to make a true Eſtimate of things, to diveſt them from all thoſe foraign and ſpacious <hi>Accoutrements,</hi> with which <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Miſtake</hi> have cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. We ſhall then ſee things in their own native and naked Forms, and be able to reduce them to their true, and intrinſick Worth and Value.</p>
            <p>The greateſt and moſt univerſal miſchief Mankind ſuffers under, is the Deluſion of a falſe and unrectifyed Imagination. This is,
<pb facs="tcp:94860:3"/> an <hi>Error,</hi> in the firſt <hi>Concoction,</hi> and gives a <hi>Tincture</hi> to all our Judgments, and a <hi>Biaſs</hi> to all the Actions of our Lives: The very Ground and Cauſe of all our Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages. We derive falſe Conceptions from our <hi>Cradles,</hi> and ſuck it in with our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Milk. Our <hi>Nurſes,</hi> &amp;c. deſtroy us in our very Infancy with their <hi>Tattle</hi> and Impertinence, which root themſelves ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our <hi>Fancies,</hi> that we can hardly, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, diſengage our ſelves from them all our Life after. Hence we contract a <hi>habit</hi> of Lazineſs, and become fitly diſpoſed to take things upon <hi>Truſt</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> to ſave the Charge of a little Examination, and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: The Spring and Riſe of all our late <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Vexation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Buſineſs of this <hi>Author,</hi> is to Inſtruct us how to become our own Maſters, and to make uſe of thoſe Faculties our <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> hath endued us with, to thoſe Ends and Purpoſes for which they were intended.</p>
            <p>The Reader upon the firſt View will find this Treatiſe to be an imitation of that exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Piece of Dr. <hi>Brown,</hi> call'd <hi>Religio Medici,</hi> however without the leaſt Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of reaching ſo brave an Original, tho not without the hopes of very nearly <hi>Reſembling</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:94860:4"/> him in ſome of his Nobleſt Flights and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies.</p>
            <p>The Principal Subject of the <hi>whole</hi> is purely diſputable, as being for the moſt part matter of <hi>Opinion,</hi> wherein it has ever been lawful to take which ſide we pleaſe: And tho he ſometimes ventures upon <hi>Myſteries</hi> of an higher nature, yet he hopes 'tis done with that Reverence and Tenderneſs, as may render him at leaſt excuſable in that behalf. For notwithſtanding, the Expreſſion may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <hi>Dogmatical,</hi> the Deſign is wholly an <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> and <hi>Experiment,</hi> and not to be taken for an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Deciſive</hi> Sentence of thoſe Matters.</p>
            <p>I ſhall foreſtall the Readers <hi>impatience</hi> with no longer Harangue, not in the leaſt doubting, but upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt reading, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to, and Approbation of this Treatiſe, will be a ſufficient Juſtification of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> and his Attempt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94860:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>RELIGIO Bibliopolae.</head>
            <p>THOUGH Trades (as well as Nations) have Scandals faſtn'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them in the Lump, yet there are ſome in all Profeſſions to whom the abuſive Character is not due. <hi rend="blackletterType">Bookſellers</hi> in the Groſs are taken for no better than a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (tho' thanks to our few <hi rend="blackletterType">Kindred</hi> among the Stars, 'tis only by prejudic'd men) yet among them there is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ail of men who are no Strangers to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Honeſty.</hi> I, that am one of that Calling, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m bold to challenge the Title of a <hi>Christian,</hi> neither am I aſham'd to expoſe my <hi>Morals.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94860:5"/>
            <p>I have no reaſon to tax my <hi>Education,</hi> or blame thoſe who had the Care of my <hi>Juvenile Years.</hi> My Tutors were Learned and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, and made it their Buſineſs to <hi>form my Mind,</hi> and <hi>ſquare</hi> my Soul by the beſt Precepts and pureſt Examples. Yet when I arrived at Years of maturer Judgment; I found occaſion to prune my ſelf, and lop off many Excreſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; to wipe out the early Impreſſions of my Infant years, and unlearn the <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions</hi> I ſuck'd in with my <hi>Mothers Milk.</hi> Tho' there were no <hi>Legends</hi> in the Nurſery, nor <hi>Hereſies</hi> in the Schools where I was brought up: Yet my blooming <hi>Phancy</hi> was fertile in <hi>Errors,</hi> and ſprouted forth in many <hi>Luxuriant Thoughts.</hi> It was the Task of my Riper Judgment to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Theſe, and reduce my ſelf to the Standard of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having therefore got the Weather-gage of <hi>Youthful Mistakes,</hi> by diligent Scrutinies, and proper Remarks; Having put in the Balance and weigh'd my <hi>Native Religion</hi> with all others that are extant, I now make that the Object of my <hi>Choice,</hi> which before was only the Effect of <hi>Prepoſſeſſion;</hi> and as I was liſted a <hi>Soldier</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in my <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſo now I decl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re my ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Volunteer</hi> in his <hi>Service:</hi> What was then done without my <hi>Knowledge,</hi> I now ratifie by my free <hi>Conſent.</hi> And I reſolve not to change my <hi>Banner</hi> as long as I live.</p>
            <p>'Tis no <hi>Soleciſm</hi> in Divinity to ſay, That the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> is the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Hosts.</hi> The <hi>Church Militant</hi> is his <hi>Army</hi> compoſed of many
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94860:5"/> 
               <hi>Bartalions,</hi> in different <hi>Posts,</hi> and under vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Orders.</hi> So long as they all ſerve the great <hi>Captain</hi> of our Salvation, and practiſe well the Diſcipline of their Arms, I refuſe not to give the word of <hi>Peace</hi> to any, let him be of what <hi>Company</hi> or <hi>Troop</hi> ſoever. The <hi>variety</hi> which we behold in the Univerſe is not its deformity, but its beauty. As the Eye is more <hi>raviſht</hi> with a Landskip which invites it with the grateful interpoſitions of Hills and Vallies, Woods and champian Grounds, than if it were let out to loſe it ſelf in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> of a waſte Horizon or <hi>empty Proſpect.</hi> So is the truly <hi>pious Soul</hi> more ſurpriz'd with the Glory of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion when various apprehenſions agree in the ſame <hi>ſubstantial Holineſs,</hi> (<hi rend="blackletterType">one Star differing from anoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r in Glory,</hi>) yet all ſhining with a light borrow'd from the ſame <hi>Fountain.</hi> And doubtleſs he is the Man who is moſt likely to be a Member of the <hi>Church Triumphant,</hi> who cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially embraces with the extended Arms of good-will, who ever are dignifi'd with the Image of Piety, tho' not diſtinguiſh'd with his own <hi>Superſcription.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I profeſs my ſelf an impartial Lover of all good men, and do preſume every man to be good till I find him otherwiſe. I have as little Zeal about things that are manifeſtly indifferent, (either <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con</hi>) as any man in the World, for 'tis a Principle I receiv'd from my Education, that the real differences of good and intelligent People are not ſo wide as they ſeem, and that through prejudice and intereſt they do many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94860:6"/> times conteſt about words, whilſt they do heartily think the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>I am not fond of the Names which diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh one Party from another in the <hi>Church.</hi> I eſteem not a man the better for being regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in this <hi>Communion,</hi> rather than in that. And for ought I know in the <hi>Camp</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> a <hi>Reformade</hi> may be as acceptable, as in thoſe of Men. However a Mutineer in either is odious, and to raiſe <hi>Factions</hi> about <hi>Religion,</hi> is to adore <hi>Mars</hi> inſtead of <hi>Christ,</hi> and to commence a War for the ſake of Peace. I cannot approve of their bitter <hi>Zeal,</hi> who, if they cannot call down Fire from <hi>Heaven,</hi> will kindle it on the <hi>Earth</hi> againſt all that think not as they do. He is an ill Diſputant for Chriſtianity, who uſes no other Topicks than Gun-powder and Steel. <hi>The Logick of</hi> Mahomet <hi>becomes not a Diſciple of Jeſus;</hi> and I ſhould make but an Hypocritical Convert, were I to be <hi>Dragoon'd</hi> into <hi>Religion</hi> by the Domineering Arguments of <hi>Booted Apostles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To perſwade to Conformity by Priſons and Confiſcations, is in my apprehenſion ſomething like demonſtrating a propoſition in <hi>Euclid,</hi> or apologizing by a Beetle and Wedges, and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they will equally produce their Effects; when any <hi>Mathematitian</hi> ſhall do the one, the <hi>Spiritual Court</hi> may perform the other. We find few edified by a Dungeon, or inſtructed by the ſpoiling of their goods. <hi>Force</hi> hath as little power on Souls as a Chirurgions Knife on the Underſtanding and Affections of men:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94860:6"/> 
               <hi>Remedies</hi> muſt have ſome Analogy with the Sick and their Diſeaſes. 'Tis ſound Reaſon (which is of our Eſſence and Conſtitution) with ſome little intermixtures of Kindneſs and Love, that muſt make men Proſelytes to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or nothing.</p>
            <p>The uſe I make of this Variety in <hi>Religions</hi> is fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> different: <hi>Truth</hi> is <hi>Homogeneous,</hi> and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts to it ſelf all that is of its own <hi>Nature,</hi> whereſoever diſpers'd or ſeparated, rejecting the reſt as not pertaining to it. Thus I over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looking the <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Mistakes</hi> of thoſe who differ from me, at the ſame time embrace their <hi>Orthodox Tenets,</hi> and ſhunning their <hi>Vices,</hi> I imitate their <hi>Vertues.</hi> This is to take Things by the right handle, and like the <hi>Bee</hi> to ſuck <hi>Honey</hi> out of every Weed. It is of the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> who has commerce with many Pollutions, yet remains himſelf undefiled.</p>
            <p>I abhor that mercenary Courſe of joyning my ſelf with any <hi>Party</hi> of <hi>Christians</hi> that is uppermoſt, to abet the prevailing <hi>Faction,</hi> and aſſert the Opinions moſt in Faſhion. This is to be a Weather-cock in <hi>Religion,</hi> pliable to every freſh Gale of <hi>Interest.</hi> Neither on the other ſide do I think it good Manners or Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to affront the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> and by a ſawcy Impertinence condemn thoſe who worſhip <hi>God</hi> in the manner preſcrib'd by the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land. In my <hi>Travels</hi> I learn'd this <hi>Moderation,</hi> and he that knows not how to practiſe it, is not fit to ſtir out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94860:7"/> of his Chimny Corner. <hi>Religion</hi> does not authorize <hi>Rudeneſs,</hi> neither is <hi>Arrogance</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible with <hi>Devotion.</hi> It is difficult to find a Company of four or five men together, where there is not at leaſt a <hi>Triumvirate</hi> of <hi>Religions,</hi> and he that will ſet up for a <hi>Dictator</hi> among them, ſhall have all their Forces united againſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>I do not value any mans <hi>Religion</hi> by his ſtarch'd looks or <hi>ſupercilious Gravity.</hi> I hate to put on an unſociable Face, or ſcrew my ſelf into an ill-humour'd <hi>Riddle;</hi> I do not angle for the <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>Saint,</hi> by magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterially declaiming againſt the <hi>Innocent</hi> Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements of Humane Life, and ranking things indifferent among the greateſt Crimes. Above all I cannot approve of thoſe who are prone to faſten <hi>Gods Judgments</hi> on particular <hi>Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> as if they alone cou'd unlock the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of the Almighty, and were the Privy-Counſellors of Heaven. No mans <hi>misfortune</hi> ſhall eſcape their <hi>Cenſure,</hi> but forgetting what our Saviour ſaid of thoſe on whom the Tower of <hi>Siloam</hi> fell, they condemn all alike, and preſume to diſtribute the <hi>Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Justice</hi> by their own falſe <hi>Weights</hi> and <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures.</hi> I am in Love with that Saying o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Plato; There is no Envy in the Deity.</hi> Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redly that Immenſe Ocean of Goodneſs ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver ceaſes to ſhow'r down his Favours and Bleſſings on all that are capable of receiving them, and he is not partial to any of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Creatures.</hi> Like the <hi>Sun</hi> he imparts his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94860:7"/> to all the <hi>World,</hi> and if any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>joyce not in his <hi>Beams,</hi> the <hi>Cloud</hi> that hind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s them is of their own raiſing. Thoſe men will hardly proſelite me, who dreſs the <hi>Deity</hi> in a frightful <hi>Figure,</hi> and then wou'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the World 'tis his <hi>Eſſential Complexion.</hi> While they exclaim againſt <hi>Pictures</hi> and <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> they themſelves commit <hi>Idolatry:</hi> They ſet up an infinite Tyrant, moroſe, arbitrary and cruel, inſtead of the Original, Increated Beauty and Goodneſs, worſhiping the <hi>Idol</hi> of their own Imagination, inſtead of the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Father of all things.</p>
            <p>I do not take Prayer to conſiſt in bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling o're the devouteſt <hi>Collects</hi> and <hi>Oraiſons</hi> of the Church without a due <hi>Application of Spirit.</hi> This is the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of Fools, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Salt</hi> or <hi>Fire;</hi> and therefore muſt needs be unſavory to <hi>God.</hi> The bended Knee, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs Looks, and even a Body proſtrate to the Ground, unleſs accompanied with a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate <hi>Fervour</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> are but Religious <hi>Compliments,</hi> and a Pious <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Such Mock-Addreſſes, I doubt, are not graciouſly receiv'd in the Court of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An equal diſlike I have for thoſe who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up ſtrange and unhallowed Flames; burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Incenſe, whoſe <hi>Compoſition</hi> is not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable; who hold not faſt the <hi>Form</hi> of ſound Words, but giving the Reins to their <hi>Tongue,</hi> ſuffer it to commit a thouſand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decencies in the Hearing of Him who made the Ear. Theſe, as well as the Former, are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94860:8"/> guilt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis;</hi> while they affron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heaven</hi> with <hi>Tautologies</hi> and vain <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions.</hi> The one through Inadvertency, the other through Preſumption. This bringing <hi>Form</hi> without <hi>Matter,</hi> That offering <hi>Matter</hi> without <hi>Form;</hi> and Both wanting the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> of ſincere <hi>Devotion.</hi> Yet I neither cenſure ſuch as uſe an <hi>allowable Form,</hi> provided it be accompanied with attentive Devotion: and leſs thoſe who addreſs themſelves to Heaven in <hi>words of their own chooſing,</hi> provided it be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd with Diſcretion and a modeſt Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Spirit. For when a man fitly qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, endued with Learning too, and above that, <hi rend="blackletterType">adorn'd with a go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Life,</hi> breaks out into a warm and well deliver'd Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Sermon, it hath the appearance of a Divine Rapture, he raiſeth and leadeth the Hearts of the Aſſembly in another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than the moſt compos'd or beſt ſtudied Form of words can ever do: And the <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wees</hi> who ſerve up all the Sermon with the ſame garniſhing, would look like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Statues, or Men of Straw in the Pulpit, compar'd with thoſe who ſpeak with ſuch a powerful Zeal, that men are tempted at the moment to believe Heaven it ſelf hath directed their words to them.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, I think not that to be the only Authentick <hi>Prayer,</hi> which is attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Senſual Raptures, and melting En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments: This is but the Smoke of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and ſoon vaniſhes; a mere Vapour or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94860:8"/> Ebullition, a pleaſing warmth of good <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and frequently the proper Reſult of a Sanguine <hi>Complexion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer is the Exaltation of the Soul, the Flight of a Sublimated Spirit: It makes Man an Angel</hi> pro Tempore, <hi>while his abſtracted Mind takes the Wing, and ſoars aloft, hover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Borders of Paradiſe. He then breaths immortal Airs, burns like a Seraphim, and flames out with Holy and defaecate Fires, like the moſt extaſi'd Orders of the Coeleſtial Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my own part, I can Pray Kneeling, Standing, or Sitting; either at my Buſineſs, or at my Repaſt; with or without Words and Ceremonies. And this I take to be the only Method of complying with St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Counſel, when he bids us Pray without ceaſing. A ſwift and Pious <hi>Ejaculation</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Times does the Office of a <hi>multitude</hi> of <hi>Words</hi> (tho' the moſt appoſite and elegant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Humane Language) ſince <hi>God</hi> underſtands the <hi>Dialect</hi> of the <hi>Heart</hi> as well as that of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Tongue,</hi> being the Architect of both.</p>
            <p>The Poſture which <hi>Pythagoras</hi> enjoyn'd his Diſciples, when they appeared before the <hi>Gods,</hi> was not without a <hi>Myſtery.</hi> He bid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem hold their Tongues revers'd; intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng thereby that they ſhould obſerve a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out <hi>Silence</hi> in ſuch Tremendous Company, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd utter no Words which were not dipt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the <hi>Heart.</hi> And I could wiſh the Advice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Solomon,</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Noſce Teipſum,</hi> were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94860:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94860:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94860:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94860:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94860:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94860:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94860:12"/> engraven on the <hi>Frontiſpiece</hi> of our <hi>Churches.</hi> 
               <q>My Son, when thou entereſt the Houſe of <hi>God,</hi> let thy words be few, and be more ready to hear, than to offer the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of Fools.</q> In all this, I aim at a <hi>Devotion</hi> that is Maſculine and Solid; Diſcreet and Humble, Sincere and Modeſt; full of <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Revorence,</hi> and the <hi>Fervor</hi> of the firſt Ages.</p>
            <p>In proper ſpeaking our very ſilent Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are eloquent <hi>Prayers,</hi> and the wants which are hardeſt to be uttered, are ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing <hi>Rhetorick with God,</hi> as oft times bring down ſwifter Relief from <hi>Heaven,</hi> than our loudeſt <hi>Letanies.</hi> Even we our ſelves are more apt to diſpoſe of our Alms to a dumb Perſon, who by being diſabled to make his Addreſs <hi>any other ways</hi> than by mute Signs, does by that Pathetick kind of <hi>Complaint,</hi> challenge our <hi>Charity,</hi> than to the common Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, who make a Trade of Haranguing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of their <hi>Money.</hi> Indeed every In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>Action</hi> of our Lives is a <hi>Prayer:</hi> but the more extraordinary Performances of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Vertue,</hi> pierce the Clouds, ſtorm the Regions above, and plunder <hi>Heaven</hi> it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (if I may ſo ſpeak) of its choiceſt <hi>Bleſſings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to <hi>Publick Prayer,</hi> I own there is a Neceſſity of uſing ſome <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies;</hi> and thoſe are the beſt which have the greateſt Efficacy to excite and regulate our <hi>Devotion.</hi> Not too Pompous and Theatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, nor ſlovenly and mean, but ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94860:12"/> the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and give it an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <hi>Beauty</hi> not a mere <hi>Pageantry</hi> of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Cuſtom of the <hi>Greek,</hi> and other <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Churches</hi> to ſeparate the Men from the Women in the Publick Aſſembly, ſeems to have ſomething of <hi>Antiquity</hi> for its Plea, tho' the diſuſe of it in theſe <hi>Weſtern</hi> Parts may make us think it a <hi>Singularity.</hi> I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy not that Sex the Liberty of Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>God,</hi> and being preſent at the <hi>Publick Solemnities;</hi> yet I grudge them a Priviledge which is ſo manifeſt an Impediment to our <hi>Devotion,</hi> as is their prating over the <hi>Pſalms, Reſponſes</hi> and other Portions of the <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi> I cou'd ſtand beſide the faireſt of that Sex in the <hi>Church</hi> unmov'd as Marble, their brighteſt Charms ſerving but as <hi>Foils</hi> to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> off the incomparable Eminency of that <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> who is adored in that Place. But when I hear them break the Bounds of <hi>Female Modeſty,</hi> whoſe greateſt Ornament is <hi>Silence;</hi> when I hear their Tongues running over the <hi>Prayers</hi> as loud, if not louder than the Men, either with a care<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs wantonneſs, or affected Gravity their Eyes divided betwixt an amorous Glance and a devout Ogle. This, I muſt confeſs, gives me Offence; 'tis an Obſtacle to my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e think the <hi>Grecians</hi> are not without Reaſon in aſſigning a particular Place of the <hi>Church</hi> to the <hi>Women,</hi> where they can neither be ſeen or heard. And this will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94860:13"/> not ſeem uncourtly or auſtere, if we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf has ſaid, I permit not a Woman to ſpeak in the <hi>Church.</hi> And in another Place, Let Women have Power on their Heads [that is, be covered or veil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed] becauſe of the Angels, or as ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it, becauſe of the young men.</p>
            <p>I wiſh for a purer <hi>Reformation</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> than we have hitherto ſeen; yet I am not for tearing up <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> by the Roots. I could be glad to ſee the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>God</hi> purged and cleans'd, the Building Repair'd and Beautified without Removing it from the <hi>Foundations.</hi> The Office of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> to me, ſeems no other ways differenc'd than thus; I look upon a <hi>Presbyter</hi> as a <hi>Parochial Biſhop,</hi> and a <hi>Biſhop</hi> as a <hi>Dioceſan Presbyter.</hi> Their Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty equal in <hi>Quality,</hi> tho' not in <hi>Quantity.</hi> The one has Power of adminiſtring the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> as well as the other: only for the ſake of <hi>Order</hi> and good <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> one is inveſted with a <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> and <hi>Superiority,</hi> of which the other is as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, if duely Elected to it.</p>
            <p>I envy not the <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Ruling Presbyters,</hi> their Temporal Honours and Riches, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wou'd I be a Leveller in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> Yet it were a deſirable thing, if there were a more equal Diſtribution of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Benefices, that the pooreſt <hi>Preaching Presbyter</hi> might have an Income that ſhould free Him from the Temptation of envying a <hi>Journey-man Carter,</hi> and other inferior Trades,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94860:13"/> who many times can boaſt of a larger Stipend than ſome of the <hi>Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Pluralities</hi> and Non-Reſidents were never heard of in the Primitive Ages, and it is a ſhame there ſhould be ſo many fat Parſonages, and yet ſo many <hi>lean Parſons.</hi> It is the Devil's Market where Church-Livings are bought and ſold, and ſuch <hi>Spiritual Huckſters</hi> deſerve to be whipt out of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I refuſe not to bow at the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> yet can give no Reaſon why I ſhould not as well bow at the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> they being both one and the ſame in the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> And that Scripture, which is made to countenance this Ceremony, ſeems to me to ſpeak no more than that in the Name of <hi>Christ</hi> all addreſſes ſhould be made to <hi>God</hi> the Father. For if it were to be literally taken, why do they who ſo receive it, bow the <hi>Head</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Knee?</hi> Beſides, I ſee no Reaſon why I ſhou'd not alſo bow at the Name of <hi>Meſſias, Chriſt, Emanuel,</hi> ſince the Redeemer of the World is called by all theſe <hi>Names?</hi> Nay, why ſhould not I pay the ſame Reverence to all the <hi>Names</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in all Languages? eſpecially to that tremendous Name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which the <hi>Jews</hi> think it unlawful to utter? 'Tis true indeed, I can comply with the Cuſtom of the <hi>Church</hi> in a thing not directly oppoſite to any poſitive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but I proteſt at the ſame time, my wiſhes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, that a Cuſtom acknowledg'd to be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, even by thoſe who moſt zealouſly plead for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts practice, were rather diſus'd, than impos'd
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94860:14"/> on men of <hi>tender Conſciences,</hi> ſince it gives ſo much <hi>Scandal,</hi> and has no <hi>Authority</hi> but that of <hi>Tradition</hi> to back it.</p>
            <p>I am naturally a Lover of <hi>Muſick,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it has an efficacy in compoſing or ruffling the Spirits, according to the various kinds of it. But I find its moſt immediate Operation is on the <hi>Phancy,</hi> and ſenſual Affections, not on the <hi>Superiour Faculties</hi> of the <hi>Soul.</hi> And therefore I ſee no uſe of it in the <hi>Church,</hi> where we come not to pay Homage to <hi>God</hi> in the ſtrength of an exalted Imagination, or to preſent him with the <hi>First-Fruits</hi> of our <hi>Paſſions,</hi> tho' never ſo refin'd, but to offer up our ſelves a <hi>Living Sacrifice,</hi> which is our Rational Service, ſince <hi>God</hi> is to be worſhip'd in <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> and not with aiery <hi>Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and carnal Raptures.</p>
            <p>Tho' the <hi>Ear</hi> is a Member conſecrated to the Service of <hi>Religion</hi> ſince <hi>Faith</hi> comes by <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> yet I cannot obſerve that my <hi>Faith</hi> is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any time encreas'd by the moſt Harmonious Leſſons on the <hi>Organ</hi> or other Inſtruments of <hi>Muſick</hi> uſed in Divine Service. Neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do I admire at the Country-man's Freak, who the firſt time he had ever been in a Cathedral hearing the Organ ſtrike up, fell a dancing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tho' he had been in a <hi>Muſick-houſe.</hi> To ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> freely, I know not why we may not praiſe <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as acceptably in a <hi>Dance</hi> as with <hi>Muſick,</hi> ſince the <hi>Jews,</hi> from whom we borrow our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for the latter, did as uſually practiſe the former; there being but little uſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94860:14"/> one without the other. To me a Chapter in the <hi>Bible</hi> is the beſt <hi>Muſick</hi> in the World, and no Melody like that of a good <hi>Sermon</hi> where the Preacher like a skilful Artiſt recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles the Diſcords of the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and between the Emblems and Types of the one, and the Subſtantial <hi>Truths</hi> and <hi>Myſteries</hi> of the other ſtrikes up ſuch a grateful <hi>Harmony,</hi> as far exceeds the beſt Conſort in the World, tho' it were as charming as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's,</hi> and made up of the whole Family of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So I am a great Admirer of good <hi>Painting</hi> and <hi>Sculpture,</hi> yet can never find them Helps, but Hinderances to my <hi>Devotion,</hi> ſince it is impoſſible for the greateſt Maſter that ever profeſs'd thoſe <hi>Arts,</hi> to draw or carve to the Life, what was never expos'd to any of his Sences, or to contrive a <hi>Figure</hi> of that which has no Reſemblance, the <hi>Inviſible Divinity.</hi> Indeed a Man's own <hi>Phancy</hi> in ſuch Caſes is the beſt Painter; and if it be lawful to make uſe of any <hi>Pictures</hi> or <hi>Images,</hi> 'tis of ſuch as our own Imagination frames: yet this is the way to become <hi>Anthropomorphites,</hi> and worſhip <hi>God</hi> under the <hi>Similitude</hi> of a Man, or to follow the Pagan Vanities and adore Him under the likeneſs of a Beaſt, or ſome other ſenſible <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure,</hi> ſince all the <hi>Ideas</hi> of that <hi>Mimick Faculty,</hi> are but the Tranſcripts of External Objects, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Maxim being truer of this than of the <hi>Intellect,</hi> That there is nothing in it which was not firſt in the <hi>Sence.</hi> The only way to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94860:15"/> have a true <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is to ſuppreſs the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of this buſie <hi>Faculty,</hi> and by withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the moſt inward Receſs of the <hi>Mind,</hi> there as in a <hi>Mirrour</hi> to contemplate that <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Eſſence,</hi> who is hid behind Himſelf (if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may ſo ſpeak) and cannot be diſcover'd but by his <hi>Back-parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is with Pleaſure that I behold Him in his <hi>Rays</hi> which ſhine in all his works, and he has <hi>caſt his ſhadow throughout the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> but I ſhould be oppreſs'd with <hi>Glory,</hi> were I capable of fixing my Eyes on that <hi>Abyſs</hi> of <hi>Splendors,</hi> before which the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Spirits</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> cover their Faces, as if they were aſham'd of their comparative Imperfections, and were not able to behold that Original and Increated <hi>Purity</hi> without a Bluſh.</p>
            <p>I have no ambition to become an <hi>Eagle</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> neither do I emulate the towring Flights of ſuch as pretend to extraordinary <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations.</hi> I had rather walk under the <hi>Piazzas</hi> of <hi>Gods Church,</hi> than on the <hi>Battlements</hi> of the <hi>Devils Chappel,</hi> leſt my Head ſhould grow gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with <hi>Enthuſiaſms,</hi> and I be blown off from thoſe Heighths and Pinnacles with ſome wind of vain Doctrine. That Father of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie was an <hi>Icarus</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> he had lofty Thoughts and ſoaring Speculations, but he flew without a Guide, he forſook the Path of his <hi>Mother</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> his Wings melted, and he had a terrible <hi>Fall,</hi> which at once bereft him of his <hi>Life,</hi> and ('tis to be fear'd) of his <hi>Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94860:15"/>
            <p>I take great Pleaſure ſometimes to find my ſelf entangled in <hi>Difficulties</hi> and <hi>Dangers,</hi> out of which I have no <hi>Skill</hi> to extricate my ſelf. I never think my ſelf ſafer than in ſuch a <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth</hi> of thwarting Events, as no <hi>Clue</hi> of my own Reaſon or Experience can lead me out. 'Tis then I can be chearful and triumph, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Deliverance is near at hand. And herein lies the <hi>quinteſſence</hi> of my Comfort, that I am thus particularly, and demonſtratively aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd of the Divine <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Protection,</hi> ſince nothing below a <hi>Miracle of Providence</hi> could untie ſo knotty a juncture of <hi>Misfortunes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were all the Paſſages of my <hi>Life</hi> publiſh'd, it wou'd be taken for more than a <hi>Romance.</hi> It is ſo full of Adventures which ſurpaſs the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Gyants, Monsters, Enchanted Caſtles,</hi> and the whole Syſtem of <hi>Knight Errantry.</hi> Such ſtrange and unexpected Eſcapes as I have made from the very Jaws of <hi>Death,</hi> exceed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Poets.</hi> And had I no other Reaſon but the Remembrance of my own <hi>Perils</hi> and <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances,</hi> it were more than enough to convince me of an unerring Eye that watches over <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</hi> This makes me chearful and eaſie in all humane Circumſtances, and reconciles me to the <hi>Stoicks.</hi> I look on all things to be govern'd by a fix'd <hi>Law</hi> and Eternal <hi>Deſtiny;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cou'd quietly ſit down with <hi>George Withers,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Nec habeo, nec careo, nec curo.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ider my ſelf as a <hi>Part</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore am never troubl'd at any thing which happens to me, ſince it comes not to paſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94860:16"/> without the Knowledge and Will of him who in all his Diſpenſations has Regard to the <hi>Good</hi> of the <hi>Whole;</hi> from which I am not excluded as a <hi>Member,</hi> and therefore muſt needs parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate of the <hi>Common Benefit,</hi> even when I think I ſuffer <hi>Damage.</hi> I am not peeviſh at a Calumny, nor waſpiſh at a loſs. When any one does me an Injury, I take a ſingular Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in forgiving him. There is ſuch a Noble <hi>Pride</hi> attends this generous <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as far ſurpaſſes the celebrated ſweetneſs of <hi>Revenge.</hi> I hate to gratifie my <hi>Paſſion</hi> the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way;</hi> and becauſe he has acted the part o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an ill Man, I muſt do ſo too or worſe, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſcope to my <hi>Rage,</hi> and executing the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt Dictates of my <hi>Fury.</hi> He is but a <hi>Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> in <hi>Morality,</hi> who to repair one Breach, makes another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and perhaps wider than the firſt. Beſides, 'tis the moſt profitable kind o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Revenge,</hi> when I turn a <hi>Wrong</hi> to an <hi>Advantage</hi> by cancelling it: ſince thereby I make a <hi>Friend</hi> of an <hi>Enemy,</hi> and if he have but the leaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Spark of <hi>Gratitude</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> my Benignity makes him not only bluſh at his Offence, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> puts him upon ſome ingenuous ſtudy how to make me amends.</p>
            <p>Hath any <hi>wrong'd</hi> thee? (ſays<note n="*" place="margin">See his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheridion.</note> 
               <hi>Quarls</hi>) b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>bravely</hi> reveng'd, ſlight it, and the work's begun, forgive it and 'tis finiſh'd. <hi>He is below himſelf that is not above an Injury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thy Brother hath privately offended thee, reprove him privately, and having loſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94860:16"/> in an Injury, thou ſhalt find him in thy forgiveneſs. <hi>He that rebukes a private fault openly ſordidly, betrays it rather than reproves it.</hi> The true way to ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Vertue is to follow it, and the beſt means to cry down anothers Vice is to decline it.</p>
            <p>Have any <hi>wounded</hi> thee with <hi>Slanders?</hi> meet them with Patience, haſty word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ranckle</hi> the wound, ſoft Language dreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s it, forgiveneſs cures it, oblivion takes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the Scar. It is more noble by ſilence to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>over an Injury, than by <hi>argument</hi> to overcome or ſpread it But in all caſes of this nature change conditions with thy Brother, then ask thy Conſcience what thou would'ſt be done to, being reſolv d, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change again, and do thou the like to him, and thy Chriſtianity ſhall never err.</p>
            <p>I eſteem it one of the moſt ſubſtantial Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of <hi>Religion,</hi> to ſubdue our <hi>Paſſions:</hi> and becauſe <hi>Anger</hi> is the moſt violent and precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, I uſe my moſt ſtrenuous Endeavours to ſtifle this in its <hi>Embryo.</hi> Other <hi>Paſſions</hi> take a gradual Riſe, and inſinuate by ſteps, but <hi>Wrath</hi> like <hi>Gun-powder</hi> takes <hi>Fire</hi> all at once, and blows a man up before he can look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him. Therefore I have by long and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous Practice labour'd to get the Victory of this turbulent Aflection, and I count it the <hi>Maſterpiece</hi> of Humane Wit to be above all <hi>Provocation.</hi> I cou'd long ago ſtop my Hand in the midſt of its <hi>Career,</hi> when aim'd at a faulty Servant, or ſcurrilous Companion, but now I can bridle the <hi>Nerves</hi> which wou'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94860:17"/> have ſtretch'd it forth, and curb the officious <hi>Spirits</hi> which were ſo ready to ſally forth on ſuch an Occaſion. I ſcorn to ſuffer my <hi>Tongue</hi> to be my <hi>Hand's Deputy,</hi> and to laviſh out in unſeemly Expreſſions, as if the Height of Man's Wit and Valour lay in a biting <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partee.</hi> Nay, I will not permit ſo much as my <hi>Cheek</hi> to change colour, my <hi>Eye</hi> to ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, or any other part of my Face to receive the leaſt impreſſion of my <hi>Reſentments,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may be perceiv'd that I am ferment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Yet at the ſame time I am not inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of an <hi>Affront,</hi> nor void of due Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on it. All that I aim at is to comply with the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Advice, <hi>To be angry and not to ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have no Pannick Fears of <hi>Death</hi> upon me neither am I ſollicitous, how or when I ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make my <hi>Exit</hi> from the Stage of this <hi>Life.</hi> Much leſs do I trouble my ſelf about the manner of my <hi>Burial,</hi> or to which of the <hi>Elements</hi> I ſhall commit my <hi>Carkaſs.</hi> I envy not the <hi>Funeral State</hi> of Great Men, neither do I covet the <hi>Embalming</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> I wonder at the Phancy of thoſe who deſire to be impriſon'd in leaden <hi>Coffins</hi> till the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> and to protract the <hi>Corruption</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Fleſh, out of which they ſhall be ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerated <hi>de Novo:</hi> as if they dreamt of riſing whole as they lay down, and carrying <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> into the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Change.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:94860:17"/>
            <p>For my Part I admire the <hi>Indian Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies,</hi> and were it not againſt the long eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht Cuſtom of my <hi>Country,</hi> wou'd ſooner bequeath my Body to the <hi>Fire,</hi> than be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hum'd,</hi> that ſo I might be ſooner reſolv'd into the <hi>Elements</hi> of which I was firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
            <p>Yet inſtead of that nearer way to Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, I can be contented to undergo the tedious Converſation of <hi>Worms</hi> and <hi>Serpents,</hi> thoſe greedy <hi>Tenants</hi> of the <hi>Grave,</hi> who will never be ſatisfied till they have eat up the <hi>Ground-Landlord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not puzzle my ſelf with projecting now my <hi>ſcattered Aſhes</hi> ſhall be collected together, neither do I for that Reaſon take Care for an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rn</hi> to encloſe them. I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atisfied, that at the laſt <hi>Trumpet,</hi> I ſhall riſe with the ſame <hi>Individual Body.</hi> I now carry about me, tho' there may not then be one of the ſame <hi>Individual Atomes</hi> to make it up, which are its preſent Ingredients. For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her are they the ſame now as they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wenty years ago. Yet I may be properly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid to have the ſame <hi>Individual Body</hi> at this Hour, which my Mother brought forth into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he World, tho' it is manifeſt, that there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſo vaſt an <hi>Acceſſion</hi> of other <hi>Particles</hi> ſince that Time, as are enough to make <hi>Ten</hi> ſuch <hi>Bodies</hi> as I had then. Which implies ſuch a perpetual <hi>Flux</hi> of the former, as 'twould be a <hi>Solaeciſm</hi> in <hi>Philoſophy</hi> to think I have one of my <hi>Infant Atomes</hi> now left about me.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94860:18"/> If after all this, I may be ſtill ſaid to have the ſame <hi>Individual Body</hi> as I had then, tho' there be not one of the ſame <hi>Individua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Atomes</hi> left in its <hi>Compoſition,</hi> why may w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not aſſert the ſame of the <hi>Bodies</hi> we ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have after the <hi>Reſurrection? Matter</hi> is on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the ſame in all <hi>Bodies,</hi> the <hi>Individuatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of it, the <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> proceeds onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the infinitely different <hi>Forms</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuate it. Thus when my <hi>Soul</hi> at the <hi>Reſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection</hi> either by its own <hi>Energy,</hi> or by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Power of <hi>God,</hi> and Aſſiſtance of <hi>Angels,</hi> ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be reinveſted with a <hi>Body,</hi> it is proper t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay it will be the ſame <hi>Individual Body</hi> have now, tho' made up of <hi>Atoms</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver before were Ingredients of my <hi>Comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> ſince not the <hi>Matter</hi> but the <hi>For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> gives a Title to <hi>Individuation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am the more willing to believe this wi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be the manner of our <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I think it not Decorous to put the <hi>Ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> on the Drudgery of <hi>Scavengers,</hi> as if it ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at that Day be their Employment to ſwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Graves</hi> and <hi>Channel-houſes,</hi> to ſift th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Elements,</hi> and take in all the <hi>Receptacles</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Dead</hi> for Mens divided <hi>Duſt.</hi> Not th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I think it impoſſible for <hi>God</hi> even this way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> accompliſh the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the <hi>Dead;</hi> tho' th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bodies</hi> of all Mankind were crumbled into <hi>Duſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and that Duſt ſcatter'd before the <hi>Wind,</hi> or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtill'd into <hi>Water,</hi> or attenuated into <hi>Air,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tho' thoſe Bodies were eaten by the Beaſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> or the Fiſh of the <hi>Sea,</hi> as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94860:18"/> thoſe Beaſts and Fiſh eaten again by Men. Tho' they ſhou'd undergo all theſe Changes and Tranſmigrations, yet were they ſtill in the great Repoſitory of <hi>God.</hi> The whole <hi>World</hi> in this ſence being but as one great <hi>Store-houſe,</hi> and all the <hi>Elements</hi> as ſo many <hi>Cells</hi> therein, ſo that whereſoever we ſhall be laid up, whether in the Bellies of <hi>Fiſhes,</hi> Entrails of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> or by various Altera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions become <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Food</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> yet the Great <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect</hi> of all Things knows where to find our ſcatter'd Remnants. But why ſhould we engage Him in ſo infinite a Task, when the Work may as well be done a nearer way? And put him to the Expence of multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Miracles,</hi> when fewer will ſerve the turn? When the Grand Alarm is given, He can ſoon fit our <hi>Souls</hi> with proper Matter for their future <hi>Bodies,</hi> out of the <hi>Elements,</hi> as well as out of their own <hi>Antiquated Embers.</hi> The <hi>Jewiſh Rabbins</hi> ſeem to deny the gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together our diſpers'd <hi>Aſhes,</hi> and aſſign the Trouble to a certain <hi>ſmall Bone</hi> in every Man's Back which they ſay, never ſuffers any <hi>Putrofaction,</hi> but remaining to the laſt Day in its Primitive Conſiſtency, impaſſible and incorruptible, is then impregnated by a <hi>Dew</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> which diffuſing its <hi>Vertue</hi> like a Ferment, not only animates and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens this <hi>Seminal Bone,</hi> but alſo attracts all the <hi>Atomes,</hi> which formerly conſtituted the <hi>Body,</hi> tho' diſpers'd in the remoteſt <hi>Corners,</hi> and moſt hidden <hi>Receſſes</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94860:19"/> marſhalling them in the ſame <hi>Order</hi> as they had before their <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> and ſo in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment recovering the <hi>Body</hi> to its <hi>Primitive State.</hi> But theſe are groſs Conceipts for <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who believe that our <hi>bodies</hi> ſhall in that great and <hi>Final Change</hi> become <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> and <hi>Immortal,</hi> being for ever diveſted of all the <hi>peculiar Circumſtances</hi> of Fleſh, and Blood.</p>
            <p>Let the manner be how it will pleaſe <hi>God,</hi> I am raviſh'd to think what a bright and ſerene <hi>Morning</hi> the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> will prove after the long <hi>Night</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> and the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing ſlumbers of the <hi>Grave!</hi> How vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and active we ſhall riſe from our Beds of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> how merry and blithe from the melancholy Regions of <hi>Horror</hi> and <hi>Silence!</hi> More ſprightly than Youth; ſtronger than Lyons; and ſwifter than Eagles! Full of Light, full of Joy, we ſhall ſoar aloft, and like well-mounted Travellers poſt it away through the <hi>Balmy Air,</hi> and liquid <hi>Skies,</hi> till we arrive at the Place of admirable <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> and be welcom'd to the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I dare not with ſome of the <hi>Jewiſh Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi> ſay that all ſhall not riſe at the great <hi>Day;</hi> much leſs will I preſume with others to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularize ſo far as to exclude all thoſe who periſh'd in <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood; or with a third ſort to confine the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> to the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as if we that are of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> were not capable of it as well as they! But above all I reject the Cenſure of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94860:19"/> 
               <hi>Talmudiſts,</hi> who ſay, that neither <hi>Bilha</hi> the Concubine of <hi>Jacob</hi> that lay with <hi>Reuben;</hi> nor <hi>Doeg</hi> that cauſed <hi>Saul</hi> to kill <hi>Abimelech</hi> and the Prieſts; nor <hi>Gehazi</hi> the ſervant of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> the Prophet, nor <hi>Achitophel, David</hi>'s prime Miniſter of State, ſhall riſe from the Dead. Theſe are the Memoirs of <hi>Hebrew Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Invidious Remarks the peculiar <hi>Hereſie</hi> of that over-weening <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I am more ſcandaliz'd at ſome <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> who will not allow <hi>Salvation</hi> to any man that is not within the <hi>viſible Pale</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> as if the Eternal <hi>Sun</hi> of Juſtice were Eclips'd to all that are out of their narrow <hi>Horizon.</hi> Surely He enlightens every man that comes into this <hi>World,</hi> and his <hi>Rays</hi> are not confin'd to <hi>Countries</hi> or <hi>Parties.</hi> He ſhines Univerſally, and no man can trace him in the <hi>Zodiack</hi> of his Mercy.</p>
            <p>I dare not 'tis true, (with <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>) canonize the Philoſophers, and place <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Heraclitus</hi> in <hi>Heaven;</hi> neither am I ſure that <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> by his learned Treatiſes of <hi>Heaven</hi> has obtain'd an Inheritance there him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. 'Tis too officious a Regard, and too bold a Charity, thus happily to diſpoſe of <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Men.</hi> On the other ſide I dread to paſs the Sentence of <hi>Damnation</hi> on all the <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Pagans,</hi> and to aver that none were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that died before the fifteenth year of <hi>Tiberius.</hi> Tho' the mere Light of <hi>Natural Reaſon,</hi> was not ſufficient to conduct them, nor al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their <hi>Morality,</hi> enough to entitle
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94860:20"/> them, to <hi>Supreme Felicity;</hi> Yet I cannot be perſwaded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the infinite <hi>Goodneſs</hi> would doom the vertuous <hi>Gentiles</hi> to the <hi>Abyſs</hi> of <hi>Miſery.</hi> Neither can any man demonſtrate, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> was not the Light of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> before his Incarnation, as well as after; And ſince <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw his Day and was glad, how do we know that <hi>Plato, Solon, Lycurgus, Pythagoras, Cyrus,</hi> and other wiſe Law-givers, Philoſophers and Kings, men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd for their <hi>Prudence, Temperance, Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, Chaſtity, Liberality,</hi> and the like Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues might not alſo be favour'd with a glimpſe of the <hi>Meſſias, the deſire</hi> of <hi>all Nations,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he appear'd in the Fleſh. Tho' we have no Records in <hi>Scripture</hi> of <hi>Hermes Triſmegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, Zoroaſter, Phocilides, Homer, Theognes, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetus, Theſeus</hi> and <hi>Hercules,</hi> yet we cannot be aſſured, but that they had <hi>Faith,</hi> and expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Redeemer</hi> to come, as well as <hi>Job,</hi> who was not of the <hi>Holy Line,</hi> but a <hi>Branch</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I conſider what Pains ſome of the wiſer <hi>Heathens</hi> have taken to find out the Truth; when I contemplate a <hi>Pythagoras</hi> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling through <hi>Aſia,</hi> and particularly conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> an <hi>Empedocles</hi> Journeying into <hi>Africk,</hi> to learn the Wiſdom of the <hi>Aegyptians;</hi> an <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great falling at the Feet of the <hi>Hebrew High-Prieſt,</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think the <hi>Heathen World</hi> to be ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the true <hi>Religion,</hi> as is commonly imagin'd. They had a <hi>Balaam</hi> to inſtruct
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94860:20"/> them, the <hi>Sybills</hi> to guide them to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a future <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and for ought I know, ſome of them might have the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of the Old Teſtament too, or at leaſt a good part of them, even before that cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Tranſlation of the <hi>Septuagint</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; ſince it was eaſie for thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> who had Commerce with the <hi>Jews</hi> to procure Copies of their <hi>Law,</hi> eſpecially when they were made Captives in <hi>Media, Aſſyria, Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>Eſther</hi> lying in the Boſom of <hi>Ahaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> a <hi>Daniel</hi> ſitting at the Right Hands of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Belſhazzer,</hi> and <hi>Darius,</hi> had fair Opportunities of inſtructing thoſe <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Monarchs</hi> in the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of the <hi>Moſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Law,</hi> and ſurely ſuch Holy Perſons wou'd never neglect ſo noble a Work as proſely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Kings and Princes of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Days of <hi>Solomon</hi> the Fame of the <hi>Jewiſh Nation</hi> had reach'd the utmoſt Parts of the <hi>Earth, Kings</hi> came from far, and <hi>Queens</hi> from the remoteſt Borders of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent,</hi> to be the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of that Royal <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> and Spectators of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur. How could then the <hi>Divine Oracles</hi> be hid from the <hi>Gentil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> or the <hi>Sacred Tradition</hi> of <hi>Shiloh</hi> to come, not be deliver'd to the inquiſitive <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>Earth!</hi> Without doubt the <hi>Eaſt</hi> ſaw the dawning of the <hi>Star</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the <hi>South</hi> could calculate his <hi>Meridian,</hi> even before he roſe. Neither were
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94860:21"/> the <hi>North</hi> and the <hi>Weſt</hi> without ſome glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merings of his Appearance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Wiſe Men</hi> that came to adore him at <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> perform'd but the Wiſhes of their <hi>Fathers,</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> of Queen <hi>Candaces</hi> made no Scruple to become a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> when <hi>Philip</hi> had convinc'd him that <hi>He</hi> of whom the <hi>Prophets</hi> had ſo long foretold, was now come in the <hi>Fleſh.</hi> Surely he was <hi>the deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Nations,</hi> the <hi>Hope</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as the <hi>Glory</hi> of his People <hi>Iſrael.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cannot number it among the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that a great Part of thoſe who profeſs that <hi>Name</hi> are ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly uncharitable, as to damn all that were not of the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> before <hi>Chriſt</hi> came in the Fleſh, as if Salvation were entail'd to one <hi>Family,</hi> and no man cou'd go to <hi>Heaven</hi> that was not circumcis'd.</p>
            <p>Much rather had I believe, That in the very Inſtant of Death, <hi>God</hi> reveal'd the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> of <hi>Redemption</hi> to many innocent and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Perſons among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and infus'd a ſaving <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> into their Souls, at the very moment that their Sences were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking their Bodies. Supplying their want of <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Tradition,</hi> with the inſpiration of his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> when they were taking the laſt gaſp, and breathing out their <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if this be not thought ſufficient, I will believe, That when <hi>Chriſt</hi> deſcended into <hi>Hell,</hi> he preach'd the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to the <hi>Spirits</hi> which were there in Priſon, not only thoſe who
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94860:21"/> were diſobedient in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> but all ſuch of the Race of <hi>Noah,</hi> as by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating the Meaſure of their Sins, had ſunk themſelves into that fatal <hi>Place,</hi> whether they were <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Heathens.</hi> And I cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thoſe <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> which men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his ſpoyling of <hi>Hell,</hi> and leading <hi>Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity Captive,</hi> if they may not be applyed to his <hi>Triumphant Deliverance</hi> of ſome of thoſe <hi>Souls</hi> which were ſhut up in the <hi>Infernal Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns.</hi> Neither do I perceive any <hi>Hereſie</hi> in believing, there might be ſome Vertuous <hi>Heathens</hi> in the Retinue he carried with Him from thence to <hi>Heaven,</hi> as well as ſome of the Sons of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> However, leaving the manner of their Salvation to <hi>God,</hi> I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That it is unreaſonable, uncharitable, and has too much of the <hi>Jew</hi> in it, to paſs the Sentence of <hi>Damnation</hi> on all the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſince the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> has aſſured us, That <hi>God</hi> is no Reſpecter of Perſons, but he that in every <hi>Nation</hi> fears Him, and works Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, is accepted of Him.</p>
            <p>Beſides, methinks if matters were brought to the ſevereſt Ballance, it would not appear Heterodox to ſay, That as all men ſin'd in <hi>Adam,</hi> without their own Perſonal Knowledge or Conſent, ſo ſome might be ſaved in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> even without a Particular and Perſonal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in Him, of whom perhaps they never ſo much as heard.</p>
            <p>Some Grains of Allowance may be given to the involuntary <hi>Frailties</hi> of <hi>Humane Nature,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94860:22"/> ſome Indulgence granted to the invincible <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> of a great Part of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity, who if they knew not the <hi>High-way</hi> to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> which was reveal'd to their Brethren the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Christians,</hi> might yet be conducted thither by ſome By-Path, ſince it is too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Conceit of <hi>God</hi>'s Mercy to think, that becauſe he had chiefly manifeſted it in the Royal Road of the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cou'd never go out of the beaten Track. This were to retrench the <hi>Divine Prerogative,</hi> and to tye Him up to limited Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, whoſe Ways are in the Great Deep, and whoſe Foot-ſteps no Created Being can Trace.</p>
            <p>The Satisfaction I have of the <hi>Soul</hi>'s <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,</hi> if it amounts not to a Demonſtration, may yet be numbred among thoſe <hi>Proleptick Ideas</hi> that need none, as being ſelf-evident. It is a Parallel with firſt Principles, and has equal Force on my Underſtanding; for I am not more convinc'd, <hi>That one and two make three,</hi> than <hi>That the Soul of man is Immortal.</hi> So that I make it not ſo much an <hi>Article</hi> of my <hi>Faith,</hi> as a <hi>Propoſition</hi> of my <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and a Concluſion of <hi>Science.</hi> Yet I do not always go ſo far round about, as by a long Train of Logical Deductions and Inferences, to diſpute my ſelf into the Remembrance of my <hi>Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> This indeed were neceſſary to perſwade another, but I have a nearer Method to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſelf with the Demonſtration of this <hi>Noble Truth,</hi> while it becomes an Object of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94860:22"/> my very <hi>Sence,</hi> and I can feel that <hi>Immortality</hi> in my ſelf, which my <hi>Reaſon</hi> tells me another is poſſeſs'd of as well as I. This is eaſier to be experienc'd, than utter'd in words, 'tis an <hi>Art</hi> not to be acquir'd without aſſiduous <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection</hi> and ſtrict <hi>Animadverſion</hi> on our own Thoughts. But the <hi>Fatigue</hi> is more than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenc'd with the ineſſable <hi>Pleaſure</hi> that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it, for when by a long and often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Practice, a man has found the way to keep cloſe Pace with his own <hi>Intellect</hi> in all its <hi>Flights</hi> and abſtracted <hi>Starts</hi> from the <hi>Body,</hi> when he can ſtand on the Brink of the <hi>Immaterial World</hi> and perceive what is before Him, perceiving alſo that he perceives it, then 'tis he enjoys <hi>Heaven</hi> by Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cipation, and foreſtalls his <hi>Future Beatitude</hi> by taſting <hi>Immortality</hi> at preſent. He is riſen from the Dead, before he dies; and lives an <hi>Eternity</hi> of Ages in a <hi>Moment.</hi> Neither is this a ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chimera,</hi> or a waking <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ream,</hi> but a real Truth, which as I have ſaid, is eaſier practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed than expreſſed.</p>
            <p>It was but a drowſie Conceit in thoſe Fathers, who phancy'd the <hi>Soul</hi> ſhou'd ſleep in the <hi>Grave</hi> till the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> Had they well traced the <hi>Nature</hi> of a <hi>Spirit</hi> from its firſt Principles, they wou'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have provided a <hi>Dormitory</hi> for That <hi>Being</hi> which wou'd ceaſe to <hi>be,</hi> ſhou'd it ceaſe to <hi>act,</hi> ſince its very <hi>Eſſence</hi> implies a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to <hi>Rest.</hi> I cou'd as eaſily and with equal Reaſon believe it will be <hi>annihilated</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94860:23"/> at its ſeparation from the <hi>Body,</hi> or at leaſt that it ſhall be <hi>metamorphos'd</hi> into ſomething elſe, ſince if it continue the ſame it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Diſſolution of the <hi>Body,</hi> it muſt continue to think, it being indeed nothing elſe but a pure <hi>Thought;</hi> and how a <hi>Thought</hi> can take a Nap, is beyond the Verge of my <hi>Philoſophy</hi> to apprehend, neither do I know of any thing in <hi>Divinity</hi> that ſeems to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſo dull a <hi>Theorem.</hi> As for thoſe Texts of <hi>Scripture,</hi> which ſeem to adumbrate the Supreme Felicity of the <hi>Saints</hi> by the Notion of <hi>Rest,</hi> I do not think they mean a Ceſſation of the <hi>Souls natural Energy,</hi> for how could it then be capable of that <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick Love,</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> in the <hi>Beatifick Viſion,</hi> which is the chief Entertainment of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>Heaven?</hi> It ſeems rather to intimate the <hi>Soul</hi>'s <hi>Eſcape</hi> and <hi>Deliverance</hi> from the Troubles and Inquietudes of this <hi>Mortal Life,</hi> which may very well be call'd a <hi>Rest,</hi> and yet be conſiſtent with an <hi>Activity</hi> far ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing that which it was endued with in the <hi>Fleſh.</hi> The <hi>Scripture</hi> clothes many ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe <hi>Myſteries</hi> in familiar Dreſſes, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to accommodate Them to the Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of vulgar and ignorant People, who make up far the greareſt Part of <hi>Mankind,</hi> and we muſt not expect the rigid Definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> from the Sacred <hi>Pen-Men.</hi> But when we come Scientifically, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Method of the Schools to treat of the <hi>Natures</hi> of Things, we ought to fit
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94860:23"/> them with proper and Intelligible Terms, and purſue their <hi>Eſſences</hi> by a continued Progreſs, not by wild Fits and Starts.</p>
            <p>I have but ſmall acquaintance with the <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State,</hi> but this I'm ſure there will be no change that will be ſo ſurprizing to me as that <hi rend="blackletterType">By Death.</hi> It is a thing of which I know but little, and none of the millions of Souls that have paſt into the <hi>inviſible</hi> World, have come again to tell me how it is.</p>
            <q>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>It must be done (my Soul) but 'tis a ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>A Diſmal and <hi>Myſterious</hi> change,<note place="margin">Norris.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When thou ſhalt leave this <hi>Tenement</hi> of Clay,</l>
                  <l>And to an <hi>unknown</hi> ſomewhere <hi>wing away;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When <hi>Time</hi> ſhall be <hi>Eternity,</hi> and thou</l>
                  <l>Shalt <hi>be</hi> thou know'ſt not <hi>what,</hi> and <hi>live</hi> thou know'ſt not <hi>how.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amazing State!</hi> no wonder that we dread</l>
                  <l>To <hi>think</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> or <hi>view</hi> the <hi>Dead,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou'rt all wrapt up in Clouds, as if to thee</l>
                  <l>Our very <hi>knowledge</hi> had <hi>Antipathy.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Death could not a more <hi>ſad</hi> retinue find,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sickneſs</hi> and <hi>pain before,</hi> and <hi>darkneſs</hi> all <hi>behind.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome courteous Ghoſt</hi> tell this great Secrecy,</l>
                  <l>What 'tis you are, and we <hi>muſt</hi> be.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou warn us of <hi>approaching Death,</hi> and why</l>
                  <l>May we not know from you what 'tis to <hi>dye?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But you having <hi>ſhot</hi> the Gulph, delight to ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucceeding Souls <hi>plunge</hi> in with like <hi>uncertainty.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:94860:24"/>
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>When Life<hi>'s</hi> cloſe knot by <hi>writ</hi> from Destiny,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> ſhall cut, or <hi>age unty;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When after ſome <hi>delays,</hi> ſome dying ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>The Soul stands <hi>ſhivering</hi> on the ridge of Life;</l>
                  <l>With what a <hi>dreadful Curioſity</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Does ſhe <hi>launch</hi> out into the Sea of vast <hi>Eternity.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>So when the ſpacious Globe was delug'd o're,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>lower holds</hi> could ſave no more,</l>
                  <l>On th' <hi>utmoſt</hi> Bough th' aſtoniſh'd Sinners stood,</l>
                  <l>And view'd th' <hi>Advances</hi> of th' <hi>encroaching</hi> Flood</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O're-topp'd</hi> at length by th' Elements encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>horror</hi> they reſign'd to the <hi>untry'd Abyſs.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>It is very deſirable to know in what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our Souls will be when they leave the Body, and what is the <hi>Nature of that abod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> into which we muſt go, but which we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw into; and through what Regions we muſt then take our flight, and after what manner this will be done. 'Tis certain my Soul will then preſerve the faculties that ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> natural to it, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>underſtand, to will, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,</hi> as 'tis repreſented to us under the Parable of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus:</hi> But alas! we little know how the People of the <hi>diſembo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died Societies</hi> act, and will, and underſtand, and communicate their thoughts to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and therefore I long to know it. What conception can I have of a ſeparated Soul (ſays a late Writer) but that <hi>'Tis all Thought.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94860:24"/>
            <p>I firmly think when a mans body is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him by Death, he is turn'd into all <hi>Thought</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> How great will be its Thought when it is without any hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from theſe material Organs that now obſtruct its Operations. In that <hi>Eternity</hi> (as one expreſſes it) the whole power of the Soul runs together one and the ſame way. In Eternity the Soul is united in its Motions, which way one faculty goes all go, and the Thoughts are all concentred as in one <hi>whole Thought</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beverley</hi>'s great Soul of Man. <hi>pag.</hi> 292.</note> of Joy or Torment.</p>
            <p>Theſe things have occaſioned great <hi>variety of Thoughts</hi> in me, and my Soul when it looks towards the other World and thinks it ſelf near, it can no more ceaſe to be inquiſitive about it, than it can ceaſe to be a Soul.</p>
            <p>I am not at all edified in the <hi>Notion</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> by the ſight of a <hi>Triangle,</hi> neither can the whole <hi>Syſtem</hi> of the <hi>Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks</hi> improve my Knowledge in this Point of <hi>Divinity.</hi> The <hi>three</hi> diſtinct <hi>Faculties</hi> of a <hi>Humane Soul</hi> are far from illuſtrating to me the <hi>Three Perſons</hi> in <hi>One Eſſence,</hi> ſince there is a <hi>Subordination</hi> in the Former, whereas there is an <hi>Equality</hi> in the Latter. Such Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes and Compariſons ſeem not to me a <hi>Stenography</hi> or ſhort Characters, but a falſe Spelling in <hi>Divinity.</hi> And tho' to <hi>wiſer Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and more <hi>Active Beliefs,</hi> they may ſerve as <hi>Luminaries</hi> in the <hi>Abyſs</hi> of knowledge, yet my <hi>Heavy Judgment</hi> will never be able to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94860:25"/> mount on ſuch weak and brittle <hi>Scales</hi> and <hi>Roundels</hi> to the lofty Pinnacles of true <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</hi> All the force of <hi>Rhetorical Wit</hi> has not Edge enough to diſſect ſo tough a Subject, wherein the little obſcure <hi>Glimmerings</hi> we gain of that <hi>Inacceſſible Light,</hi> come not to us in <hi>direct Beams,</hi> but by the faint <hi>Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of a <hi>Negative Knowledge.</hi> And we can better apprehend what <hi>it is not,</hi> than what <hi>it is.</hi> In the Diſquiſition of his Works, I own, that thoſe do highly magnifie Him, whoſe <hi>Judicious Enquiry</hi> into his <hi>Acts,</hi> and deliberate <hi>Reſearch</hi> into his <hi>Creatures</hi> return the Homage of a Devout and Learned <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe.</hi> But in the Contemplation of that <hi>Eternal Eſſence</hi> to which no created Thought can be adaequate, I will humbly ſit down and ſilently admire, that which neither the Heart can conceive, nor the <hi>Tongue</hi> or <hi>Pen</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Angels</hi> can declare as they ought, and as it is.</p>
            <p>I do not affect <hi>Rhodomontadoes</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> nor to boaſt of the <hi>Strength</hi> of my <hi>Faith:</hi> I do not covet Temptations, nor court Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: Yet I can exerciſe my <hi>Belief</hi> in the difficulteſt Point when call'd to it; and walk ſtedfaſt and upright in Faith, without the <hi>Crutch</hi> of a viſible <hi>Miracle.</hi> I can firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> without going in <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> to his <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> neither need I the <hi>Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> that was vouchſaf'd to St. <hi>Thomas</hi> that <hi>Proverb</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief.</hi> However I do not bleſs my ſelf, nor eſteem my <hi>Faith</hi> the better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94860:25"/> I lived not in the <hi>Days</hi> of <hi>Miracles,</hi> nor ever ſaw <hi>Chriſt</hi> or any of his <hi>Diſciples.</hi> Or becauſe I was not one of his <hi>Patients</hi> on whom he wrought his <hi>Wonders.</hi> Both their <hi>Faith</hi> and mine were infus'd by the Miniſtration of the <hi>Sences.</hi> And as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve't becauſe they <hi>ſaw,</hi> ſo I believe, becauſe I <hi>hear</hi> (undenyable Witneſſes give <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of) the ſame <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Fact.</hi> Nor do I eſteem their <hi>Faith</hi> the more <hi>Extraordinary</hi> who lived before his Coming, ſince they raiſed not a <hi>Belief</hi> of the future <hi>Meſſias,</hi> but on clear <hi>Propheſies,</hi> and moſt ſignificant <hi>Types,</hi> being aſſured by the conſtant ſtream of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> from Father to Son, that what <hi>God</hi> had predetermin'd and foretold to <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> ſhould infallibly be accompliſh'd in the fulneſs of Time. And I cannot ſee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their <hi>Faith</hi> had the Advantage of ours, that it ſhould deſerve to be eſteem'd more Bold and Noble, ſince they had an <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to preach the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to Them, who for the Eloquence of his Style, his moſt accurate and particular Enarration of the <hi>Birth</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> has acquired the Title of the <hi>fifth Evangeliſt.</hi> 'Tis certain both their <hi>Faith</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ours reſts on the <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> whether it conſiſt in <hi>Propheſie</hi> of Things to come, or <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of Things paſt. The ultimate <hi>Object</hi> of our <hi>Belief</hi> is one and the ſame, that is, the <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> They had their <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> alſo to ſtrengthen their Faith as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94860:26"/> well as we. They were <hi>Baptized</hi> in the <hi>Cloud</hi> and in the <hi>Sea,</hi> they had <hi>Manna</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Water</hi> out of a <hi>Rock</hi> in the <hi>Earth.</hi> They all eat the ſame Spiritual Meat, and drank the ſame Spiritual Drink as we, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they drank of the Spiritual <hi>Rock</hi> of Ages that followed Them, and that <hi>Rock</hi> was <hi>Chriſt</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not conclude from hence, That ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is, no difference between the <hi>Sacraments</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Law,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there is an Excellency in the Latter to which the Former could not pretend The <hi>Elements</hi> in Both are <hi>Natural,</hi> as <hi>Wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Manna, Bread, Wine,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teriour, neither of Them has the Advantag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the other. They were both alſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits of the ſame inward <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> Only herein lyes the difference, that the <hi>Jews</hi> had it but by Meaſure, whereas th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſtians</hi> receive it in Abundance. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> touch'd but the Hem of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Garment but we feed on his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did but wade in the low Ebb of <hi>Grace</hi> whereas we ſwim in the High-Tide an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> over-flowings of the <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> Before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Everlaſting Sluces were drawn up; whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Heavens</hi> were kept ſhut, the <hi>Water</hi> which are above the <hi>Heavens</hi> did but diſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gently on Mankind, The Divine Influenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> came Drop by Drop, here a little and ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a little. But when Chriſt had once aſcend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed up on High, and open'd the <hi>Eternal Gate</hi> above, then he ſhowr'd down his Gifts upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:94860:26"/> Men, and let looſe the Flood of Light and Grace, that ſo it might water the whole Earth, and <hi>make glad the City of God,</hi> which is the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sacraments of Chriſtianity</hi> are the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Channels through which Eternal Life is conveyed to our Souls. By <hi>Baptiſm</hi> we are tranſplanted from the Old Stock of the <hi>Firſt Adam,</hi> and inoculated into Him who is the <hi>True Vine,</hi> in whom we grow up as Branches, receiving Nouriſhment and Encreaſe by the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> which conveys to us the vital Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Immortality</hi> and Salvation. I cannot ſpeak of this tremendous Myſtery, without a <hi>Circumlocution,</hi> nor think of it without a <hi>Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture!</hi> It is ſuch a <hi>Complex of Riddles,</hi> as it hath pos'd the ſtouteſt <hi>Samſons</hi> of the Church to ſolve: He alone was able to think and ſpeak aright of it in <hi>few</hi> words, who when he firſt inſtituted it, ſaid, <hi>This is my Body, This is my Blood.</hi> That there is a real <hi>Change</hi> made in the outward Elements after the words of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration are pronounc'd, is an <hi>Article</hi> of my Faith; but the Manner how <hi>this Change</hi> is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected is no Query of my <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humbly believe what I cannot comprehend in this Venerable <hi>Sacrament;</hi> than ſuffer any vain Diſquiſitions to ſtagger my Faith. I ſee <hi>Bread and Wine</hi> both retaining the ſame Taſte, Colour, and other natural Qualities of thoſe Creatures. Therefore I conclude there is no <hi>Alteration</hi> made in that which is the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of my <hi>Sences.</hi> The Change muſt be in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94860:27"/> 
               <hi>Spiritual Part,</hi> which only falls under the Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. And yet I believe this <hi>Change to be Real,</hi> tho' I cannot ſenſibly perceive wherein, or how 'tis produced. Far be it from me to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Secret of thoſe who make a mere <hi>empty Figure</hi> of the Bleſſed Sacrament; as if we were made Partakers only of mere <hi>Natural Bread</hi> and Wine in the Holy Communion. This is to follow the impious Steps of <hi>Manicheus and Marcion,</hi> who taught that our Saviour had only a Fantaſtick Figure of a Body, not a Real one; as if they thought the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> brought forth nothing but a Shadow, becauſe ſhe was overſhadow'd by the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>This is to outstrip</hi> Judas, <hi>and begin where his Treaſon left off:</hi> and as he ſold his Maſter's Life, ſo we ſhould rob the Church of his <hi>Body and Blood,</hi> which he bequeath'd to her in his laſt Supper. Doubtleſs his Body is in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Euchariſt, but not <hi>Bodily,</hi> or after a corporeal manner, not inveſted with all the groſs Circumſtances of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> but after a Spiritual Manner, in a <hi>Myſtery</hi> too pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found for <hi>Humane Sence</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. I am extremely pleas'd with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> gave to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> when he demanded her Opinion of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> ſaid ſhe,
<q>
                  <l>'Twas God the Word that ſpake it,</l>
                  <l>He took the Bread and brake it;</l>
                  <l>And what the Word did make it,</l>
                  <l>That I believe and take it.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:94860:27"/>
            <p>It was an ill-manner'd, as well as an envious Retort of him that ſtood by and ſaid, Your Highneſſes Reply is like the <hi>Delphick Oracle,</hi> full of Ambiguous Subtilty: He had diſcover'd more Breeding and Charity, had he told her, That her Anſwer ſavour'd of his Wiſdom, who, when tempted by the <hi>Phariſees</hi> with a Queſtion concerning the Lawfulneſs of paying <hi>Tribure to Caeſar,</hi> took a piece of Money and asked <hi>whoſe Image and Superſcription</hi> was that ſtamped on it, they ſaid Caeſars, He replyed, <hi>Give therefore to Caeſar, the Things that are Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar's,</hi> and to God the Things that are Gods. It is certainly a neceſſary piece of Prudence ſometimes to obviate the <hi>Trains</hi> of an Enemy, with a witty Evaſion; which may be done without denying the Truth, or violating ones Conſcience. Thoſe who wou'd <hi>trepan a man with Queries,</hi> and make him a Tranſgreſſor for a word, deſerve to be paid in the ſame Coin, and by an <hi>Ingenious adapting</hi> of words and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Periods, be baſſled in their Deſign, and ſent away like Fools as they came, without any better Satisfaction than they cou'd reap from <hi>a Riddle.</hi> In my Opinion it is but a Pious <hi>Scepticiſm</hi> to ſuſpend our Thoughts from determining the particular Mode of Chriſt's being <hi>preſent</hi> in the Sacrament, ſince it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible ever to demonſtrate ſo recondite a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, into which even the Angels themſelves, thoſe <hi>perfect Intelligences</hi> perhaps look with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, without improving their Knowledge. It is ſufficient to my <hi>humble Faith,</hi> that my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94860:28"/> is there, and that when I worthily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this Bleſſed Sacrament, I ſhall receive the Author of it into my Tabernacle, and be united to the Heavenly Spouſe. This is the true <hi>Hidden Manna</hi> which nouriſhes both An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men; This is the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> which ſtrengtheneth Man's Heart; This is the Wine which rejoyceth God and Man. This is that <hi>Heavenly Morſel</hi> which God has given us as an Antidote againſt the Dregs of that Venom we all derive from <hi>Adam</hi>'s eating the forbidden Fruit.</p>
            <p>And he is a <hi rend="blackletterType">kind Phyſician,</hi> who, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in the Divine <hi>Pharmacopaea</hi> could be ſound available for ſo great a Cure, <hi>applies his own Body,</hi> to heal the Diſtempers of our Souls, and his Blood to reſtore the <hi>Spoyls of Humane Nature.</hi> None but the Favourites of the King of Heaven are admitted to this <hi>Immortal Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</hi> None but ſuch as have the Wedding Garment on, can have Acceſs to this Table of Delicacies, this Repaſt of <hi>Royal Dainties.</hi> Many indeed (and too many, 'tis to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) are licenſed to come into the <hi>Kings Anti-Chambers,</hi> and to ſit down in the Church and taſte the <hi>outward Elements,</hi> but it is the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Saints only to enter his Cabinet, and be <hi>Regal'd</hi> with the coſtly Entertainment of his Secret Table, and to partake in the New Wine of the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>A Serious Chriſtian once told me, that if ever he was like <hi>Paul</hi> taken up into the <hi>Third Heaven,</hi> it was when he firſt ſat down at the Lords Table.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:94860:28"/>
            <p>The Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> is the neareſt and <hi>viſiblest</hi> Communion that can be had with God and Chriſt upon Earth. Here are the greateſt revivings and the ſweeteſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhings that a Pious Soul is capable of on this ſide Heaven it ſelf. Other Duties ſeem to be our work, this our <hi>meat and wages,</hi> other duties are but preparative to this, <hi>Baptiſm, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Preaching, Hearing, Meditating, Conferring,</hi> are all ordained but to ſit us for this High and Myſterious Ordinance. Here you have all the benefits of the Covenant of Grace folded up in one Rite. Here is the <hi>whole contrivance of Salvation repreſented in a little Bread and Wine,</hi> whereby God inviſibly ſeals up an aſſurance of his Everlaſting Love upon our Hearts.</p>
            <p>It is grown even to a Proverb, ſaith <hi>Acosta,</hi> among the poor <hi>Indians</hi> that have entertained the Faith that <hi>Qui Euchariſtiam ſemel ſuſcepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He muſt never more be unholy that hath once received the Holy Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Poſture of Receiving,</hi> I am not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, being willing to conform to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of thoſe with whom I <hi>communicate:</hi> I can receive on my <hi>Knees</hi> without Danger of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; or <hi rend="blackletterType">Sitting,</hi> without the Guilt of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. This latter I eſteem of greater Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, it being the Poſture wherein <hi>Chriſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to his Diſciples</hi> at the laſt Supper, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be ſaid they <hi>lay along</hi> according to the Mode of the Eaſtern People in thoſe Days. However I do not think the <hi>Poſition</hi> of the Body, but the Preparation of the Soul is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94860:29"/> to render one a <hi>Worthy Commun icant</hi> in theſe Holy Myſteries.</p>
            <p>I cenſure not the Primitive Chriſtians, not thoſe more <hi rend="blackletterType">Modern</hi> ones, who Communicate frequently, yet I ſhould be timorous to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach theſe <hi>Holy Myſteries</hi> too often, leſt I ſhould incur the Judgment which St. <hi>Paul</hi> has pronounced on thoſe who <hi>eat and drink unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</hi> I have Charity for others who Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate this Sacrament Monthly, Weekly, or <hi>Daily,</hi> but I ſhould have little for my ſelf, ſhould I receive this tremendous Myſtery of Life, with leſs Preparation than were <hi>requiſite to fit me for Death.</hi> It being in the Number of thoſe Medicines which either <hi>Kill or Cure,</hi> according to the Conſtitution to which they are applyed.</p>
            <p>If we examine the Books of Phyſicians, thoſe <hi>Regiſters of Humane Frailty</hi> and Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, we ſhall find no leſs than <hi>Six Thouſand Diſeaſes</hi> on the Score, to which Man's <hi>Body</hi> is liable. And 'tis to be feared the <hi>Diſtempers of the Soul</hi> come not ſhort of the Account. What is Pride but a <hi>Tympany?</hi> Luſt but a <hi>Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver?</hi> Drunkenneſs but a <hi>Dropſie?</hi> Envy and Malice but the <hi>Conſumption</hi> of the Soul? To obviate theſe and innumerable more Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Maladies, God has (as a Token of his Infinite Bounty) given His Miniſters Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to diſpenſe to the Sons of Men the <hi>Sacrament of his Body and Blood,</hi> as a Divine Catholicon, or Cure for [all] the Diſeaſes which are incident to our Souls, but with this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94860:29"/> Condition, That he who partakes of theſe <hi>Holy Myſteries</hi> unworthily, inſtead of being healed, does but increaſe his Malady, work it up to a dangerous <hi>Criſis,</hi> if not to a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Paroxiſm,</hi> which affords no Hopes, but a fearful Expectation of <hi>Judgment to come. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> tells us two remarkable Stories, that one coming to the Sacrament, after the Miniſter had given him the <hi>Bread,</hi> and he going to eat it, it ſtuck in his Throat <hi>Gladium ſibi ſumens non cibum,</hi> ſaith he, he received his Bane inſtead of Bread, the other came and took the Bread into his Hand, and when he went to eat it, there was nothing but <hi>Aſhes in his Hand.</hi> This Apprehenſion, I ingenuouſly declare, has had ſuch <hi>Influence</hi> on me, as to reſtrain me long from approaching the <hi>Holy Table.</hi> I tremble at the Thought of <hi>Eating and Drinking my own Damnation,</hi> and of trampling under-foot the Blood of the <hi>Eternal Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I love not to humour my <hi rend="blackletterType">Spleen</hi> or gratifie my <hi>Hypocondria,</hi> by inveighing againſt the Luxury of the <hi>preſent Age,</hi> as if it were worſe than thoſe of old, and that our <hi>Fore-fathers</hi> did not Eat and Drink to Exceſs as well as we: The preſent Intemperance of Mankind is but the <hi>Tranſmigration of the Former:</hi> And our Poſterity ſhall but act o're the Patterns we ſet them. <hi>Drunkenneſs is as old as</hi> Noah<hi>'s Flood, and Epicuriſm begun with</hi> Adam. The one had no ſooner eſcaped the Univerſal Inundation of <hi>Water,</hi> but he had like to have been drown'd in a <hi>Deluge of Wine;</hi> And the Other
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94860:30"/> not content with the large Indulgence and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion God had given Him to eat of the <hi>Fruits of Paradice,</hi> muſt needs <hi>leap the Fence</hi> which guarded the <hi>Forbidden Tree,</hi> and whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he might have Banquetted without Satiety or End on the <hi>Varieties</hi> which would have given him <hi>Life and Immortality,</hi> he plays the Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and Surfeits Himſelf with the Plant of Death and Damnation. His <hi>Children</hi> ſoon learn'd to tread in their Father's Steps, and <hi>Gluttony was equally propagated with Mankind.</hi> And tho' that <hi rend="blackletterType">Repairer</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi>'s almoſt Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt Progeny could he abſtemious, when he might have furniſht his Table with all the <hi>Beaſts of the Earth and Fowls of the Air at one Meal,</hi> yet he could not refrain from the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Fruit of the Vine.</hi> His Ebriety was alſo catching, and the Inceſtuous Off-ſpring of <hi>Lot</hi> ow'd their Original to the <hi>Blood of the Grape.</hi> Before the Flood Men were buſied in Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting and Riot, ſo they have been ever ſince, and ſo they will be, to the End of the World. Men are great Followers of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in the Practice of theſe Vices.</p>
            <p>For my Part I envy not the <hi>Board of</hi> Vitellius that at one Meal was covered with <hi>two Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Fiſh,</hi> and double that Number of <hi>Fowls.</hi> Neither do I covet the more Expenſive Feaſts of <hi>Heliogabulus.</hi> The refin'd Luxury of <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra</hi> ſeems to me leſs Sordid, tho' more Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal, who at one Draught <hi>ſwallow'd down a King's Ranſom.</hi> It was not her Palate ſhe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd in that Rich Potion, but ſhe humour'd
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94860:30"/> the Guſt of her Ambition; which is a <hi>Sublimer ſort of Vice,</hi> and may not unfitly be call'd the <hi>Gluttony of the Soul,</hi> while it Revels on the Breath of Fame, and Epicurizes with a <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melion-like</hi> Appetite on the Air of Honour.</p>
            <p>Intemperance is the <hi>Blind ſide of Mortals;</hi> it is our ſoft Place, where we ſuffer our ſelves to be ſtroak'd and tickl'd to Death by the <hi>flattering</hi> Serpent. This made <hi>Iſaac</hi> miſ-place his Bleſſing for a <hi>Piece of Veniſon,</hi> and his Son to ſell his Birth-right for a <hi>Meſs of Pottage.</hi> The <hi>Italian</hi> Proverb hits the Glutton Home when it ſays, He digs his Grave with his Teeth, and cuts his Throat with the Knife that carves his Meat.</p>
            <p>Rioting and Drunkenneſs were formerly eſteemed the National Sin of <hi>Germany</hi> only, but I believe other Nations may put in for a ſhare in the Charter. <hi>It is the Epidemick Vice of the whole World.</hi> Men fall paſſionately in Love with it as if they were of <hi>Mucaus</hi> the Poet's Opinion, who held, That <hi>perpetual Drunkenneſs</hi> was the only Reward of Merit and Vertue. The very <hi>Mahometans</hi> themſelves, who are expreſly forbidden by their Law to <hi>taſte</hi> of Wine, being told by <hi>Mahomet</hi> that there is lodg'd a <hi>Devil in every Grape,</hi> are ſworn Votaries to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and the greateſt Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards on Earth.</p>
            <p>For my own Part, I could be content with the Diet of <hi>Johannes de Temporibus,</hi> who when he had lived three Hundred years, being ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the King of <hi>France, What method</hi> he took
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94860:31"/> to preſerve his Life to ſo great an Age; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>Intus Melle, extra Oleo.</hi> I ſay, I could be content with his Diet, not ſo much for the ſake of <hi>Spinning out my Life</hi> to Centuries of years, (which yet I believe were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together impracticable in one of my Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution) as that by a conſtant and habitua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Deſuetude of <hi>merely Animal</hi> Enjoyments, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might the more cloſely and vigorouſly atten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Operations of my Soul, and be always <hi>awake to the Superiour Faculties of my Mind</hi> and Intellect, <hi>Anima Sicca, eſt Anima Sapiens,</hi> was a true Maxim of the Philoſopher. And the Sons of <hi>Minerva</hi> experience it.</p>
            <p>I abhor the Superſtitious Cant, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminating Shibboleth of <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> who muſt needs take upon them to alter the Form of ſound Words; as if the Dialect of the Primitive Church were grown obſolete, or that the Apoſtles underſtood not the <hi>Orthogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy of Chriſtian Faith.</hi> I like not thoſe Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Bouteſeus,</hi> who take a great Deal of Pains to breed a Quarrel between <hi>Religion and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and ſet thoſe two Twins together by the Ears; as if we could not be good Chriſtians, unleſs we deny our <hi>Senſe and Reaſon.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is not the Buſineſs of Religion to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant and Extirpate Nature, but to prune and rectifie it. <hi>Religion</hi> is that which poliſhes and ſmooths the Roughneſs of laps'd Humanity, pares away the Vicious Knobs which grow up with us from our <hi>tainted Embryo,</hi> and by various Inſtruments of Grace forms and ſquares
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94860:31"/> us into ſit Materials for God's Holy Temple. <hi>The Work of Regeneration ſeems in ſome manner to copy that of Creation.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt at his firſt Viſit, finds us in our corrupt ſtate, but a meer <hi>Chaos,</hi> a confuſed <hi>Heap of Paſſions</hi> and Senſual Appetites; our Reaſon, that <hi>Light of our Souls</hi> lyes Dormant, ſmother'd as it were by our Animal Faculties; Darkneſs covers the Face of this <hi>Microcoſm,</hi> till he give the Word, <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> and by a forcible Energy ſtrike ſome Divine Sparks out of our <hi>Flinty</hi> Hearts: Thus ſeparating the <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſtial</hi> Parts from the <hi>Terreſtrial,</hi> and Sublimating us into the Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itude of his own glorious Eſſence, Enduing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s with <hi>Faith,</hi> without deſtroying our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd inſpiring us with Charity, without exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating our Paſſions. Thus I can believe the moſt tranſcendent <hi>Myſteries</hi> of our Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd yet not be guilty of an implicite Credulity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd blind Devotion: And I can practiſe <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ian Moderation,</hi> tho' I cou'd never learn the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>toical Apathy.</p>
            <p>I highly value the Sacred Scripture as the <hi>Oracle of Divinity, and Rule of Faith:</hi> Yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſteem them not a Syſtem of Philoſophy, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pandect of <hi>natural Science.</hi> They are able <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o make us Wiſe unto Salvation, and perfect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Knowledge of God, through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, but they inſtruct us not in <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ane Curioſities,</hi> nor acquaint us with the Theory of all his Works. That frightful Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on of the Apoſtle <hi>[Beware of vain Philoſophy]</hi> no Bug-bear to my Studies, nor can it ſtartle
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94860:32"/> my harmleſs Enquiries into the <hi>Secrets</hi> of the Elements. I will not be afraid of prying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Circumſtances of the <hi>Earth,</hi> ſince <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> has told us, it is <hi>hang'd upon Nothing;</hi> nor <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> caſting my Eyes up to the Heavens, and exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mining the Motions, Influences and Oper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, of <hi>the Sun, Moon and Stars,</hi> ſince t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſame Holy Patriarch was poſed with this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrological Queſtion by God himſelf, Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thou <hi>reſtrain the ſweet Influence of the Pleiad<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or looſe the Bands of Orion?</hi> There are ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Natural Obſervations in the Bible which m<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſerve as Hints or Spurs to more <hi>accurate D<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiſitions:</hi> But in no Place that I know o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> does it ſet a <hi>Non Ultra</hi> to thoſe Sober Enqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers, who by making a Modeſt and Judicio<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Search into the <hi>Works of the Creation,</hi> are c<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pable of returning a more exact and conſum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mate Praiſe to the Eternal <hi>Architect</hi> Indee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt (if not all) the <hi>Manual Trades</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> World, are but the ſeveral <hi>Species</hi> of Pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal Philoſophy: While the Mechanick pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Execution the <hi>Theory</hi> of the Student, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what the One dictates from the <hi>School of <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture,</hi> the other Experiments in the <hi>Shop <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Art.</hi> Neither would Men know how to ke<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> themſelves in Action or maintain Commerc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were it not for the Sake of <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this are owing all the Advances and <hi>Progreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons</hi> that Ingenious Men have made in the Callings and Occupations. And every <hi>Smit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Carpenter, Maſon, &amp;c.</hi> that makes an Im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>provement in his Craft or Myſtery deſerve
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94860:32"/> the Tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> and to be number'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Philoſophers</p>
            <p>Among all the Sciences, there is none to which (had I leiſure) I could be more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted than to <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> and for this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I cou'd raiſe a Pyramid to the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the <hi>Teleſcope,</hi> That Happy Midwife to new Diſcoveries in the Heavens; and think my Self no leſs oblig'd to Him that firſt found out the <hi rend="blackletterType">Motion of the Earth.</hi> Both have Enfranchis'd me from the Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Prepoſſeſſion, and taught me to <hi>unthink</hi> the Sentiments of my greener Years. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I owe no Allegiance to <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and am perfectly wean'd from the Magiſterial Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of the <hi>Stagyrite.</hi> I cannot ſo readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe that the <hi rend="blackletterType">Sun</hi> moves above two Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Miles every Minute of Time, as that the Earth moves Eighteen Miles in that ſpace. And that the <hi>Planet Saturn</hi> moves ten, and the <hi>fixed Stars</hi> a Hundred Times faſter and farther than the Sun in the ſame ſpace, which muſt be the Conſequence of the <hi>Earth's ſtanding ſtill,</hi> and the Suns Motion. It ſeems no <hi>good Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> to me, to expect that from Gods Infinite Power, which is repugnant to his equal Wiſdom and the <hi>Laws of Motion</hi> which he has Eſtabliſh'd in the Univerſe. This were to make one of his Attributes <hi>Claſh</hi> with another, and to calumniate his Holineſs, which conſiſts in the <hi>Harmony</hi> of them all. I adore his <hi>Omnipotency,</hi> and tremble at the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94860:33"/> Thought of calling in Queſtion the Power that made <hi>All things of Nothing.</hi> Yet I think it my Duty to be wiſe as well as Devout, and to ſpeak <hi>rightly</hi> as well as <hi>reverently</hi> of his Divine Perfections. As his word is the <hi>Rule of my Faith,</hi> ſo his Providence is the <hi>Pole-Star</hi> of my Reaſon. And in the Scrutiny of his Works do not ſo much enquire what he is able to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as what he uſes to do. Being aſſured tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as nothing is to him Impoſſible, ſo he has ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Being, Actions, Paſſions, Qualities and Circumſtances of all Things, ordering them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> exact Number, Weight and Meaſure. So that <hi>à poſſe Dei ad eſſe Rei non valet Conſequentia.</hi> He has fix'd the Laws of <hi>Loco-motion</hi> in Corporea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Subſtances, and ty'd up the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> it ſelf to a certain Proportion of Time and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which it can no more exceed, than the ſmalleſt <hi>Wheel</hi> of a Watch.</p>
            <p>Such prodigious <hi rend="blackletterType">Whirligigs,</hi> as the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bodies muſt needs be, in the <hi>Ptolomaick Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis,</hi> makes me giddy to think on't, and I believe they were troubl'd with a Vertigo, that firſt <hi>reel'd</hi> upon the Notion: Or they l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd under the Deception of thoſe at <hi>Sea,</hi> who ſailing within Sight of the Shore, and not being able to perceive the Motion of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel that carries them, are apt to phancy the Neighbouring <hi>Cliffs, Towns and Trees</hi> were under Sail, and ſteering a contrary Courſe, ſince they ſo appear to do. For not leſs ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently do I believe the <hi>Earth moves conſtantly round on her Axis,</hi> thus making the Natural
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94860:33"/> Day and Night, without putting the whole Frame of the Univerſe into an unconceivable Hurry.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Planet Jupiter</hi> is diſcover'd by the Teleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope to make the ſame Circulation in 10 Hours, <hi>Mars</hi> in 23, and the <hi>Sun</hi> himſelf in 28 Days. Theſe are no Chimaera's or Dreams of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, no Metaphyſical Speculations of <hi>Nut-ſhell</hi> Brains, but Real Truths, demonſtrable by Art and Ocular Experience. And methinks it is a more <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform Idea,</hi> if we ſuppoſe the <hi>Earth to be a Planet</hi> like the Reſt, and to take its Turn in the Septenary Dance round the Sun, who is plac'd in the Centre of this Vortex, and is the <hi>true Apollo,</hi> to whoſe Muſick the whole <hi>Planetary System</hi> keeps Time. I fear not the Laſh of <hi>Maurolycus,</hi> nor the Scourge of his bigotted Brethren. If <hi>Copernicus</hi> was by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem thought <hi>Scuticâ &amp; Flagello dignus,</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovating on the Doctrines of <hi>Ptolomy;</hi> What was <hi>Ptolomy</hi> himſelf worthy of, who entrench'd on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greater Antiquity, and undermin'd the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſophy of <hi>Ariſtarchus Samius,</hi> who taught the <hi>Motion of the Earth</hi> above four hundred years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore <hi>Ptolomy</hi> was an Infant? For my Part I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hink it no <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt the Common-wealth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Learning to ſay, I prefer <hi>Galileo</hi>'s <hi>Tube</hi> to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tolomy</hi>'s <hi>Spectacles,</hi> and the Diſcoveries of our Engliſh <hi>Royal Society,</hi> to the blind Conjectures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Peripateticks, and the wild Speculations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Athen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I was firſt inform'd that there were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcover'd <hi>four new Stars moving about Jupiter,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:94860:34"/> and three about Saturn,</hi> I was as well pleaſed, as they who received the earlieſt News of <hi>Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi>'s <hi>landing in America.</hi> I am ſo far from being of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Humour, that inſtead of <hi>weeping,</hi> I ſhould heartily rejoyce could I be credibly ſatisfied, That there are <hi>ten Thouſand more Worlds,</hi> than are already diſcover'd.</p>
            <p>I am naturally Melancholy, and the weigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this <hi>leaden</hi> Complexion does ſo depreſs my Spirits, That all the Race of Mankind or Earth ſeems too ſmall to afford <hi>Variety</hi> enoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for a Relief. This makes me the more willin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to believe what my Reaſon ſuggeſts to be true That the <hi rend="blackletterType">Planets are Inhabited.</hi> It is a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as well as a Rational Notion; and ſince the are Dark, Opake Bodies, like the Earth w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tread on, having no other Light but what the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> borrow from the <hi>Sun,</hi> and ſeem in all othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Circumſtances to be <hi>adapted for Habitations,</hi> ſee no Solaeciſm in Philoſophy, nor Hereſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> againſt the <hi>Faith</hi> to believe they are <hi>really I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>habited</hi> as is this Globe. That they have <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> of Day and Night, and their <hi>Satellites</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Moons to give them Light by Night, even a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we, is demonſtrable to the Eye by the help o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Teleſcope.</hi> But there would, in my Opin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, be little need of all this, were there <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rational Inhabitants in thoſe Coeleſtial Globes.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is a faſtidious Pride in Man to phancy all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Glittering</hi> Furniture above was only made fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ornament, or for <hi>Shepherds</hi> to gaze on in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Night, or for ſome other Inferior uſes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sons of <hi>Adam.</hi> And 'tis a narrow Concei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:94860:34"/> to imagine, that tho' this Globe be plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Inhabited by all ſorts of Animals, <hi>not a Turf of Land, nor a Puddle of Water being without its Tenants,</hi> yet all thoſe ample and glorious Bodies above ſhould lye empty and vacant, tho' ſome of them be far bigger than our Earth, and for ought we know, may be ten times <hi>more commodious</hi> for Habitation. Thoſe Paſſages in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles to the <hi>Philippians</hi> 2.11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.9, 10. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.16. ſeem to be calculated for the <hi>Inhabitants of thoſe Heavenly Bodies.</hi> And his Emphatical words in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.9. ſeem to be but a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of the Revelations he receiv'd, and of the Things he ſaw when he was <hi>Rapt into the Third Heaven, viz.</hi> That there are ſome in thoſe Heavenly Places, even Principalities and Powers, to whom the manifold Wiſdom of God in Chriſt was made known, and that they were not only Created by Him, but for Him, and that they and we are <hi>all of one Family or Deſcent.</hi> Theſe may be ſome of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which that Holy Apoſtle ſpeaks of in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. Words and Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which could not be utter'd. And for ought I know, thoſe Beings which he calls <hi>Principalities,</hi> Powers, Mights, Thrones and Dominions may be no other than the ſeveral <hi>glorious Colonies</hi> of the Coeleſtial Family dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Stars, who all believe in the ſame Eternal Jeſus, even as we do, and through his Mediation make their Approaches to God the Father. This may be <hi>the farther Fellowſhip of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94860:35"/> the Myſtery of God, hid from the Beginning.</hi> This the untraceable Riches of Chriſt, which put St. <hi>Paul</hi> to an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. O the Depth of his Wiſdom! O the Superlative Greatneſs of his Power! But whether the <hi>Planets be Inhabited</hi> or no, this <hi>I</hi> am aſſured of, and can produce an Hundre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Authentick Witneſſes, that they are <hi>Dark</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies, like the Earth we tread on, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they have no Light but what they receive from the Sun, which alſo they do but partially en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy like us, by <hi>Succeſſive</hi> Hemiſpheres, having their Day and Night meaſur'd out to them proportionate to the Time they take up in moving <hi>round their Centers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I have tyred my ſelf with following theſe <hi>viſible Motions of Nature,</hi> I retire <hi>Home</hi> again, thinking to take Sanctuary in my ſelf, and find a Reſt in the Contemplation of my own <hi rend="blackletterType">Soul:</hi> But there I do but commence a new Fatigue, and am hurried about in a <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> Circle by an inviſible Energy within me. I think, ſpeak, and act with <hi>infinite Variety,</hi> yet know not how I perform theſe different Operations. I know my ſelf to be an <hi>Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real</hi> Subſtance, and can eaſily <hi>feel</hi> out my own Independency on the Body. I look on this <hi>Houſe of Clay</hi> I carry about with me, to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my Priſon. But how I am confin'd to this Priſon, I that am but a poor Scintillation or Spark of the Eternal Sun, is a <hi>Riddle</hi> which I cannot ſolve. I can better imagine how a Beam of our Viſible Sun may be united to a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94860:35"/> Marble Statue, than that a <hi>pure Thought</hi> ſhould be faſtned to a Clod of Earth, from which it cannot free it ſelf but by Death, though it can pervade all the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> beſide. What Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is it that thus cloſely tyes together two ſuch incompatible Eſſences, as <hi>Heaven and Earth,</hi> Light and Darkneſs, Spirit and Body? This is a Knot muſt be left for <hi>Elias</hi> to untye, and is indeed one chief Argument of the <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack</hi> of Humane, Reaſon, ſince not only all other Things are obſcure to us, but we are ſo to our ſelves, the neareſt Objects, even our own <hi>Domeſtick</hi> Operations are as incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to us, as thoſe that are fartheſt off. The Things that touch us, nay the very Faculties by which we <hi>touch, ſee, underſtand, &amp;c.</hi> are as diſtant from us as the <hi>Ninth</hi> Sphere, &amp; we are as much ſtrangers to our ſelves, as to the Inhabitants of <hi>Terra Incognita.</hi> There wou'd be nothing more welcom to me than a <hi rend="blackletterType">Hiſtory of my Original,</hi> for I do not compute my Age or Family, by the ſhort Chronology of the <hi>Pariſh-Regiſter;</hi> nor do I think my ſelf much the older by my Mother's Additional Record of <hi>Nine Months,</hi> I liv'd in her Womb. I eſteem her Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from my <hi>Conception,</hi> but the Tragick Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of my Death, and thoſe which by moſt are accounted the <hi>Chambers of Life,</hi> and Shops of Generation, are no better in my Judgment than the Receptacles of the Dead, Seminaries of Corruption, the Graves of Souls <hi>defunct to the Higher World.</hi> For I believe I was then Born when the Morning Stars <hi>Sang together,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:94860:36"/> and when all the Sons of God ſhouted for Joy. I time my <hi rend="blackletterType">Infancy</hi> with that of the Univerſe, and eſteem no Man older or younger than my ſelf, no not the <hi>Angels</hi> themſelves, believing that all <hi>Spiritual</hi> Subſtances were Created toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Beginning. I will not with ſome accuſe <hi>Moſes</hi> of ſcantineſs in his <hi>Hiſtory of the Creation,</hi> becauſe according to the Letter he ſeems to take but little notice of <hi>Immaterial</hi> Beings. The Hebrew <hi>Cabbala,</hi> with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries of their Learned Rabbins, and ſome of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Fathers of the Chriſtian Church do ſufficiently evince, That there are greater Myſteries contained in the Three firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> than the bare Letter, or Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Tranſlations ſeem to exhibit. There is a <hi>Sacrament</hi> in that Holy Language, which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever partakes of, can be no ſtranger to the Natural and Divine Truths couch'd under it. To ſuch an One the Hiſtory of the <hi>Terreſtrial Adam</hi>'s Happy State in Paradiſe, and his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment from thence, will be an Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick of the Original Beatitude of the Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial World, and the Degeneracy of humane Souls, their Deſcent from the Aetherial Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and <hi>Conſinement to Houſes of Clay,</hi> as well as of the Fall of Angels. I ſeem to my ſelf, not without Reaſon to embrace the Doctrine of the <hi rend="blackletterType">Praeexiſtence of Souls,</hi> ſince it was among the <hi>Credenda</hi> of many Antient Sages, a peculiar Tradition of the Jews, and the general Opinion of all the Eaſt. That Queſtion which was put to our Saviour concerning the <hi>Man
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94860:36"/> that was born Blind,</hi> whether it was for his own ſins, or thoſe of his Parents, ſeems clearly to imply, That he was in a Condition or Capacity of <hi>ſinning before his Birth,</hi> which how it could be without ſuppoſing the <hi rend="blackletterType">Praeexiſtence</hi> of his Soul, is paſt my Divinity or Philoſophy to unriddle. The various Conjectures alſo which the Jews made of Chriſt, according to the Report of his Diſciples, when ſome <hi>ſaid he was</hi> Elias, <hi>others that he was one of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, a third ſort, that he was</hi> John <hi>the Baptiſt riſen from the Dead,</hi> are evident Arguments, That the Doctrine of Praeexiſtence, and a <hi>Metempſychoſis</hi> was eſtabliſh'd as part of the Creed of that Nation. Of which alſo that paſſage in the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> is no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure hint, where the Author ſays, <hi>Or rather being a good Spirit, I came into a Body pure and undefiled.</hi> Neither am I ſtartled becauſe I find not Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles aſſerting, or ſo much as mentioning any ſuch Doctrine. St. <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Hyperbole</hi> in the laſt verſe of his Goſpel, ſatisfies me, that I muſt not expect to find all that our Saviour did and ſaid, regiſter'd by the Evangeliſts: And St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s frequent Exhortation to hold faſt the Traditions that he had imparted to them, whether by <hi>Word</hi> or <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> convince me, That it is not unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to conclude, That he deliver'd many Doctrines in his Sermons, which he had no occaſion to mention in his <hi>Letters to the Churches:</hi> Among which this might be one. However, it is a ſufficient Warrant to my
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94860:37"/> Belief, That I no where in all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures can find this Doctrine reprehended. Which, had it been an Errour, cou'd not have eſcaped the cenſure of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; it being the Univerſal Tenet of all ſorts of Jews, except the Sadduces. When I conſider alſo that <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Ammonius</hi> taught it in the Schools of <hi>Alexandria. (Plotinus</hi> himſelf learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it from the latter) and that all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Fathers who were Platoniſts, aſſerted it not only as a Philoſophical, but alſo as a Divine Truth; I look upon it as an Effect of <hi>Gothick Barbarity</hi> and Ignorance, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards overſpread all Chriſtendom, That nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this, nor hardly any other <hi>Point of Platoniſm</hi> were countenanced in the Chriſtian Schools, but only the Dictates of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his <hi>Ghoſt Averroes.</hi> In fine, that elegant Flouriſh of St. <hi>Auguſtine, Infundendo creatur, creando in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funditur,</hi> is no Rule of my Faith in this Point, ſince it faſtens ſo many irreverend Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences on God Almighty; neither can I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Soul to be <hi>ex Traduce,</hi> becauſe it carries in its <hi>Front</hi> ſo many <hi>Inconſiſtencies</hi> in Philoſophy, beſides the Indignity that is done to the Soul thereby, which amounts to a true <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> ſince 'tis levell'd at the whole Order of <hi>immaterial Beings.</hi> I muſt therefore believe, That I had a Being <hi>long</hi> before I came into this Body, and yet not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Manner of my Exiſtence into a meer <hi>Potentiality,</hi> or an unactive ſlumber in the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of my Cauſes,</hi> as if I were then but a <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94860:37"/> Idea</hi> in the Blood of my Fathers, or a <hi>Metaphyſical Dream</hi> of my preſent ſelf. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I was in a State of greater Activity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was <hi>conceiv'd</hi> by my Mother than ſince ſhe bore me; and for ought I know, have <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rang'd all the Boundleſs Tracts of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, been Naturaliz'd in the ſeveral Regions of the Sky and Air, till being tyred with ſo vaſt a Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and willing to try all States of Life,</hi> I was by the Force of a ſtrong Inclination, and the irreſiſtible Charm of rightly adapted Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>allured</hi> into this Terreſtrial Body, here to do <hi>Penance</hi> for the Faults of my Superiour Life, and in this Horizon between the upper and the lower World to make my Choice of Good or Evil, Light or Darkneſs, Life or Death. This unlocks all the <hi>Aenigma's of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence;</hi> and reconciles the harſher Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with which the Immediate Creation or Traduction of Souls is involved. It is the nobleſt Inſtrument of Vertue, the ſharpeſt <hi>Spur</hi> to a Divine Life, whilſt it doubles the Hope; we have of being Immortal <hi>à Parte poſt,</hi> by aſſuring us we were ſo <hi>à Parte ante.</hi> And that it is not from any Arbitrary Decree of God, inconſiſtent with the Reſt of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections, that we ſhall live for ever, but from our own Nature and Eſſence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Created to ſubſiſt an <hi>interminable</hi> Duration of Ages.</p>
            <p>I believe thoſe Books of the Holy <hi>Scripture</hi> which are loſt, could they poſſibly be recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, would ſerve as a Lamp to enlighten
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:94860:38"/> us in many <hi>Obſcurities</hi> of Religion, Hiſtory, and Nature: And if the Writings of <hi>Jaſher, Idd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Prophet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> could inform us nothing of the <hi rend="blackletterType">Praeexiſtence</hi> of Souls, 'tis very probabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the more early Oracles of <hi>Enoch</hi> would, ſinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he was but the <hi rend="blackletterType">Seventh Soul <hi>that was drench'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Terreſtrial Matter,</hi>
               </hi> and led ſo pure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt a Life, as wou'd tempt one to believe, That he was <hi>awaken'd</hi> to the Memory of his former State, which for ought we know, might have no ſmall influence on his ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Change.</p>
            <p>I have often wonder'd where St. <hi>Jude</hi> had ſo particular an Account of <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angels diſpute with the <hi>Devil</hi> about the <hi>Body of Moſes,</hi> that he was able to relate the very words that paſs'd between them. Surely the Jews had ſome Books, or at leaſt Traditions, which were believed to be Orthodox, tho' they were not ſo much as mention'd in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Canon; for we cannot without great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety imagine that the <hi>Holy Saint</hi> wou'd impoſe upon our Belief any thing that was Forreign or Apocryphal. I am apt to conclude from hence, That there were many <hi>Traditional Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> entertained among the Hebrews, which are by us eſteemed no better than Fables.</p>
            <p>However, tho' I am thus convinced of the Truth of our <hi rend="blackletterType">Praeexiſtence,</hi> and that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life is but a <hi>Shadow or Dream</hi> in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what we enjoy'd before our Immerſion in the Fleſh; yet I wou'd not have this Dream interrupted by any untimely or harſher ſtroke of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94860:38"/> Deſtiny. <hi>I ſhou'd think it no inconvenience to live long!</hi> but rather a Bleſſing, That ſo a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of years might <hi>ſcum</hi> off the Froth and Sullage of our Appetites and Paſſions, that ſo being <hi>gradually</hi> wean'd from thoſe low Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which brought us down to the Earth, we may without any Diſquiet or Turbulency re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to our <hi>Aetherial Homes.</hi> For I am apt to think that thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouls who go out of their Bodies, with any <hi>remaining Reliſh</hi> upon them of the Body, like Fruit that is either pluck'd off, or ſhaken down by violent Winds, ſtill retain in their ſeparation, a raw and eager ſmack of the Fleſh, with a languiſhing Byaſs toward it. Whereas he that has tarried his full Period, in the Body, parts from it with Eaſe and Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs, as <hi>Ripe Fruit</hi> drops from the Tree. And therefore I do not wonder that the moſt general Scene of <hi>Apparitions, Ghoſts,</hi> &amp;c. is the Church-yard, or at leaſt that Place where the Body of the <hi>Spectrum</hi> was buried. And the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved Earth which covered the <hi>Cobler of</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia<hi>'s Body</hi> is a ſhrewd intimation, That there are ſome <hi>Departed</hi> Souls, which if they ſeek not a Reunion with their Bodies, yet endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to hold a <hi>kind of Correſpondence</hi> with them even in the Grave. And tho' the Impoſſibility of being married again to theſe their dear <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts,</hi> after that final Divorce, were enough, one wou'd think, to cure their Impotent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, yet they burn with a new Luſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a <hi>Spiritual</hi> Adultery in the unlawful Bed of the Grave. Theſe I look on as the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94860:39"/> Effects of a <hi>too early</hi> and violent Separation and therefore eſteem <hi>Methuſelah</hi> and the Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Fathers before the Flood, happy; who prolong'd their years to the <hi>utmoſt</hi> ſtandar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Humane Life, and ſeem'd not ſo much t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> die, (for that imports Violence) as volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to forſake their <hi>old Rotten</hi> Habitation ſhake Hands with their Bodies, and ſo retu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the Aetherial Palaces, from whence they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo long <hi>ſtragled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding the great Eſteem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have of <hi>long Life,</hi> as a Means rather to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove than Impair us; I cannot promiſe my ſelf to out-live a <hi>Jubilee,</hi> tho' I have already ſeen one Revolution of <hi>Saturn.</hi> Neither do <hi>I</hi> affect to make <hi>Popes, Emperours, Kings, and Grand Seigniours,</hi> the Land-marks in the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology of my ſelf; That were to inſult over the <hi>Royal</hi> Aſhes of Princes, beſides the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition in <hi>Ranking</hi> my ſelf in their Number. Methinks I grow old even at thoſe Years when the World counts me Young, and poſſeſs the Heritage of <hi>David</hi>'s laſt <hi>Ten Years</hi> of Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore, in the <hi>Prime</hi> of my Age.</p>
            <p>Indeed the whole Earth, and all this <hi>Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary World</hi> ſeems to droop and decay. Every <hi>Species</hi> of Beings grow weak and languid, and ſeem to draw near their Diſſolution. Yet 'tis needleſs to engage God in the Act, ſince tho' <hi>Creation</hi> was above the Force of Nature, yet <hi>Mutation</hi> is not, and no <hi>Annihilation</hi> can proceed from that Paternal Eſſence of Eſſences. It ſeems eaſie to me to believe, That the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94860:39"/> World will periſh upon the <hi>Ruins of its own Principles.</hi> And tho' the preciſe Period of its Deſtruction be not known to the Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elves, yet there are not wanting ſome <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical Rules,</hi> whereby one might venture to Calculate its Duration, and by obſerving the various Attempts, Eruptions and Devaſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made by <hi rend="blackletterType">Fire</hi> already, one may conjecture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bout what Time that moſt <hi>active</hi> Element <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall be let looſe, to deſtroy this Face of the World, and transform this <hi>Superannuated</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en and Earth into <hi>New Ones,</hi> as the Holy Prophet has foretold. For as to Annihilation, look on it as a Chimera, or Non Entity, which cannot be ſaid to ſlow from Him who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>All-being,</hi> and the Fountain of Exiſtence. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t were eaſier to conceive that Cold ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the immediate Effect of Fire, and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs the Natural Reſult of the actual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence of Light, than to think that <hi>Annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion or not Being</hi> can proceed from Him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho is the Original Source of Being, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe Divine Power, Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs all Things flow by a <hi>Neceſſary Emana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> and continue in their ſeveral Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns by as unalterable a Law as that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave them; ſo that there can be no Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſuppoſed in their Eternal Subſiſtence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Leaps or Starts from Something to No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing. It is far more agreeable to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ples of Philoſophy to conceive, That only <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Groſs and Corruptible Part of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſe ſhall be ſubject to the <hi>Action of Fire,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:94860:40"/> ſuch as the Earth we tread on with the other Planetary Bodies; but that the <hi rend="blackletterType">pureſt Aethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſhall remain for ever untouch'd, unchang'd the Sanctuary of the Bleſs'd, the Habitatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Spirits of <hi>Juſt men made perfect.</hi> I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo confirmed in this Belief by ſomethi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more Sacred and Authentick than <hi>natural</hi> Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. For when the Royal Pſalmiſt in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Divine Rhapſody calls upon the <hi>Heavens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heavens, and the Waters which are above t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Heavens</hi> to praiſe God, he gives this for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reaſon, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Becauſe he ſpake and the were made, he commanded and they wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> created. He eſtabliſh'd them to Eternit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>for Everlaſting Ages:</hi> He fix'd a Decree which he will not diſannul. Then he calls upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Earth and all Creatures therein to joyn i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame <hi>Act of Praiſe,</hi> but not for the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reaſon; not becauſe the <hi>Earth ſhall endu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for ever,</hi> but becauſe the Name of God alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is exalted, and his Honour above Heaven an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Earth. Which Diſtinction ſeems to me a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> evident Argument of the <hi>unalterable Stabili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Coeleſtial and Aetherial World,</hi> what<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever Mutations and Changes the Terreſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may be ſubject to.</p>
            <p>That thoſe immenſe Tracts of quiet and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſible <hi>Aether</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Seat of the Bleſs</hi> is very conſiſtent with Philoſophy, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ways repugnant to Divinity. However, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Place be where it pleaſes God, we ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſſured that the Entertainment and Joys <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> far ſurpaſs all humane Comprehenſion. Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:94860:40"/> tho' we cannot have <hi>adequate</hi> Conceptions of Supream Felicity, there are ſome Land-marks by which we may take imperfect Meaſures of that <hi>Region of Promiſe.</hi> The Dim-Light of Natural Reaſon may afford us a Glimpſe, or faint Proſpect of thoſe Superlative Joys, and the <hi>Opticks of Faith</hi> will improve the View. We ſhall have the ſame Nature and Faculties there as here, but free from the leaſt Alloy of Frailty and Imperfection. Our Souls ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play the radiant Brightneſs of their Immortal Eſſence with ſtronger <hi>Vibrations</hi> than the Sun, having no <hi>internal Scum</hi> of Concupiſcence boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out from the Center of a depraved Will or erroneous Underſtanding, to blemiſh and ſtain thoſe unſpotted Orbs of Light; nor a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene groſs Body to Eclipſe and ſhut up their Splendors. But being ever Bright and Serene, they ſhall <hi>ſhine through</hi> their Glorified and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Bodies, as the Sun does through the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ervious</hi> Air, or at leaſt as he does on a <hi>Bright</hi> Cloud, which drinks in his Beams to reflect them abroad with a more <hi>ſenſible</hi> Glory. We ſhall then ſee, not by receiving the Viſible Species into the <hi>narrow Glaſs</hi> of an Organized Eye, we ſhall then hear without the diſtinct and curious <hi>Contexture</hi> of the Ear. The Body ſhall then be <hi>all Eye,</hi> all <hi>Ear.</hi> All <hi>Senſe</hi> in the whole, and every Senſe in every Part. In a word, it ſhall be all over a common <hi>Senſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> and being made of the pureſt Aether, without the Mixture of any lower or groſſer Element, the Soul ſhall by one <hi>undivided</hi> Act,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94860:41"/> at once perceive all that Variety of Objects which now cannot without ſeveral diſtinct Organs, and ſucceſſive Actions or Paſſions, reach our Senſe. From this <hi>Superlative</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity and Claritude of our Bodies, will ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>ineffable</hi> Delicacy in the Senſation of the Soul, which will tranſport it with Deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> infinitely tranſcending the <hi>Heighth</hi> of Mort<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Voluptuouſneſs, nay and even thoſe more ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alted Pleaſures which the Vertuous ſometime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enjoy here on Earth as <hi>Foretaſts</hi> of their futur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Beatitude in Heaven. What here excites bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an Ordinary Emotion of Joy in the Soul, wi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> there produce all <hi>Raptures and Ecſtaſies.</hi> We ſhall be always in <hi>Paroxiſms of Love,</hi> ſuch are the tranſcendent <hi>Beauties</hi> of that admirable Place! and ſuch the divinely amorous Bent of the Soul. We ſhall be <hi>always languiſhing,</hi> yet ever enjoying what we languiſh for: Neither ſuffering the leaſt Pain through the Want of Fruition, nor through any Satiety that ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it: But through the <hi>Vigour of an Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Activity,</hi> we ſhall have ever freſhly kindle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Deſires and new Enjoyments, being diſſolv'd in a <hi>Circle of Beatitude</hi> without Meaſure or End.</p>
            <p>Here on Earth Men generally ſtrive to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolize</hi> Pleaſure to themſelves, there being few of ſo generous a Temper as to be ſenſibly touch'd with Delight, that another ſhou'd par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with them in that which they eſteem Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity: This is the <hi>peculiar</hi> Advantage of the Bleſs'd in Heaven, that even in the Heighth of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94860:41"/> the Affairs of Immortal Love and Empire, where they poſſeſs <hi>Eternal</hi> Crowns and unfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Beauties, there is no ſuch Thing to be found as a Rival or Competitor, but every <hi>one's Joy</hi> is enhanc'd by the Enjoyments of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. <hi>Every one loves all, and all love every one.</hi> Neither wou'd their Felicity be Perfect, cou'd any Member of that Happy Society be ſuppos'd not to have his full proportion and ſhare of Beatitude. So communicative is the Love and Joy of thoſe Holy Souls, that they muſt ceaſe to love and enjoy themſelves, ſhou'd they deſiſt from loving and rejoicing in the Happineſs of their <hi>Fellow-Citizens.</hi> And if we may take our Meaſures of their Joys from our Common Experiences here on Earth, it will be no ſmall Augmentation of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency, to find thoſe <hi>very Friendſhips which they had contracted here below,</hi> tranſlated to the Manſions above, when they ſhall both ſee and know thoſe whom they once loved on Earth, how to be made Denizens with them in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>with what Ardours will they careſs one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her!</hi> With what Tranſports of Divine Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection will they mutually embrace, and vent thoſe Innocent Flames, which had ſo long lain <hi>ſmothering</hi> in the Grave! How paſſionately Rhetorical and Elegant will their Expreſſions be, when their Sentiments which Death had <hi>Frozen</hi> up, when he congeal'd their Blood, ſhall now be <hi>Thaw'd again in the warm Airs of Paradiſe!</hi> Like Men that have eſcap'd a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Shipwrack, and ſwim ſafe to the Shore,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94860:42"/> they will congratulate each other's Happineſs with Joy and Wonder. <hi>Their firſt Addreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will be a Dialect of Interjections and ſhort Periods the moſt Pathetick Language of Surprize and high wrought Joy!</hi> And all their after converſe eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Eternity, will be couch'd in the higheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Strains and Flowers of Heavenly Oratory, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Allelujahs intermix'd.</p>
            <p>It much <hi>ſweetneth</hi> the thoughts of Heave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to me to remember that there are a multitu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of my Friends gone thither; to think ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Friend that died at ſuch a time, and ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at another time <hi>(O! what a number of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cou'd I name)</hi> and that all theſe I ſhall meet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gain. 'Tis true, <hi>it's a queſtion with ſome wheth<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhall know each other in Heaven</hi> or no? b<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 'tis none with me; for ſurely there ſhall <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Knowledge ceaſe which now we have, b<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> only that which implyeth our Imperfectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and what Imperfection can this imply? Inde<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we ſhall not know each other <hi>after the fleſh,</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by Stature, Voice, Colour, or outward Shap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor by Terms of Affinity and Conſanguini<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> nor by Youth or Age, <hi>nor I think by Sex,</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the Image of Chriſt and Spiritual Relatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beyond doubt we ſhall know and be know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor is it only my old Friends (ſuch as <hi>Eſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ruſſel, Sydney,</hi> &amp;c.) that I ſhall know in He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven, but all the Saints of all Ages, who Faces in the Fleſh I never ſaw. <hi>Luther</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laſt ſickneſs being ask'd his Judgment wheth<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we ſhall know one another in Heaven, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwer'd thus, <hi>Quid accidit Adamo? nunquam i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:94860:42"/> viderat Evam, &amp;c. i. e.</hi> How was it with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</hi> he had never ſeen <hi>Eve,</hi> yet he asketh not who ſhe was, or whence ſhe came, but ſaith, <hi>She is Fleſh of my Fleſh, and Bone of my Bone.</hi> And how knew he that? Why, being indued with the true knowledge of God, he ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced; after the ſame ſort ſhall we be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by Chriſt in another Life. And we ſhall know our Parents, Wives, Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> much more perfectly than <hi>Adam</hi> did then know <hi>Eve.</hi> In Heaven we ſhall not only ſee our <hi>Elder Brother Chriſt,</hi> but all our Kindred and Friends that living here in his fear died in his favour, for ſince our Saviour tells us that the Children of the Reſurrection ſhall be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> equal to,<note place="margin">Luke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.36. Luke 16.</note> or like the Angels who yet in the Viſions of <hi>Daniel</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> appear to be acquainted with each other, ſince in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the <hi>miſerable Epicure</hi> and the happy Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar the Father of the Faithful is repreſented, as knowing not only the Perſon and preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but the paſt ſtory of <hi>Lazarus:</hi> Since the Inſtructer of the Gentiles confidently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects his converted and pious <hi>Theſſalonians to be his Crown at that great day:</hi> Since theſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, beſides divers others are afforded us by the Scripture, we may ſafely conclude that we ſhall know each other in a place where, ſince nothing requiſite to happineſs can be wanting, we may well ſuppoſe that we ſhall not want ſo great a ſatisfaction as that of being <hi>knowingly happy in our other ſelves, our Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:94860:43"/>
            <p>Thus far we may venture to ſpeak of the lower Degrees of Coeleſtial Beatitude, the <hi rend="blackletterType">mutual Love and Entertainment of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> But who has ever mounted to the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Scale of Heavenly Bliſs? Let him come down and tell us the Myſteries wrapt up i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Clouds, the Secrets hid within the Veil of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>acceſſible Light! Let him deſcribe the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Beatifick Viſion, and ſay how dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Rivers of Pleaſure are which run by God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Right Hand for evermore! For my Part, I muſt confeſs, I'm loſt in that Abyſs of Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and therefore modeſtly withdraw my Pen to Subjects more <hi>Domeſtick</hi> and within ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reach, and yet even here I ſhall but paſs from <hi>one Abyſs to another,</hi> ſince every Thing has a Depth in it not to be fathom'd by our weightieſt Senſe or moſt ſolid Reaſon.</p>
            <p>I have often try'd to dive into the <hi rend="blackletterType">Profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of Death,</hi> but ſtill I find my Intellect too light a Plummet, and the whole <hi>Thread of Life,</hi> though ſpun out in fineſt Speculations wou'd ſtill prove far too ſhort to reach that endleſs Bottom.</p>
            <p>'Tis true there have been men that have tryed even <hi>in Death it ſelf</hi> to reliſh and taſte it, and who have bent their utmoſt Faculties of Mind to diſcover what <hi>this paſſage is;</hi> but they are none of them come back to tell us the <hi>News.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:94860:43"/>
               <l>— No one was ever known to wake,</l>
               <l>Who once in Deaths cold Arms a Nap did take.</l>
               <bibl>Lucret. Lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Canius Julius</hi> being condemn'd by that <hi>Beaſt Caligula,</hi> as he was going to receive the ſtroke of the Executioner, was askt by <hi>a Philoſopher,</hi> Well <hi>Canius,</hi> ſaid he, whereabout is your Soul now? What is ſhe doing? What are you thinking of? I was thinking, replyed <hi>Canius,</hi> to keep my ſelf ready, and the Faculties of my Mind ſettled and fix'd, to try if in this ſhort and quick inſtant of Death I could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>motion</hi> of the Soul when ſhe parts from the Body, and whether ſhe has any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment at the Separation, that I may after come again to acquaint my Friends with it.</p>
            <p>So that I fancy there is a certain way by which ſome Men make Trial <hi>what Death is,</hi> but for my own part I cou'd ne're yet find it out.</p>
            <p>I have ſometimes thought what would I give for the <hi>leaſt glimpſe</hi> of that inviſible World which the firſt ſtep I take out of this Body will preſent me with, and that there was nothing in the <hi>whole diſcourſe of Death</hi> that I durſt not mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the boldeſt way, and have therefore of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten attempted to <hi>look him full in the Face,</hi> that I might learn to die generouſly, but ſtill when it came to the pinch <hi>Conſcience that makes Cowards of us all,</hi> made one of me, and I was forc'd to ſhrink back with ſhame.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:94860:44"/>
            <p>Yet ſurely the Terrour is not ſo much in <hi rend="blackletterType">Death it ſelf,</hi> as in the <hi>Tragick Pomp</hi> that goes before and after it. The tedious Diſcipline of Sickneſs, the formal Viſits of Relations and Friends, their melancholy Chat, the fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Harangue</hi> of the Phyſician, and our own diſmal Apprehenſions compoſe that horrid Scene which renders Death uncomfortable. When the poor Patient that perhaps may yet <hi>outlive his Fears of Death,</hi> and ſee Millions drop into the Grave before him, yet dies a Thouſand Deaths in his Hag-ridden Phancy, and makes his Bed his Grave by ſtrength of an abus'd Imagination.</p>
            <p>'Tis only Fancy gives Death thoſe hideous Shapes we think him in, for indeed Death is no more than a ſoft and eaſie Nothing, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Natures play-day.</hi> I firmly think it is no more to die than to be born, we felt no pain coming into the World; nor ſhall we in the act of leaving it, though in the firſt one would believe there were more of Trouble than in the latter, for we <hi>cry coming into the World,</hi> but quietly and calmly leave it. What is Death <hi>but a ceaſing to be what we were, before we were, we are kindled and put out; to ceaſe to be and not to begin to be is the ſame thing. Methinks it is but th' other day I came into the World, and anon I am leaving it; for though I am but in my thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year, and at preſent in perfect health and ſtrength, yet I look upon my ſelf as a man that has one foot in the Grave already, for</hi> David <hi>ſays ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty is the Age of man, and I have lived near
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:94860:44"/> thirty years of that time already. The longeſt of my</hi> deſign's now is not above a years extent, I think of nothing now but ending, take my laſt leave of every place I depart from; <hi>alas! there is no fooling with Life when it is once turn'd beyond thirty. Silence</hi> was a full anſwer of him that being ask'd what he thought of Humane Life, ſaid nothing, turn'd him round and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht. <hi>Oh how Time runs away!</hi> and we are dead e're we have time to think our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, <hi>one</hi> doth but Breakfaſt here, another Dine, he that liveth longeſt doth but Sup, we muſt all go to Bed in another World, <hi>therefore good night to you here, and good morrow hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed our whole Life is but one often <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Stop</hi> to Death, and we are as near it at the <hi>firſt Minute</hi> of our ſetting out as at a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years end. For Death either keeps an even <hi>Collateral</hi> Pace with us from our very Birth, or at leaſt he marches but <hi>one Step be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind us</hi> all the way of our Life; ſo that when the appointed Time is come for him to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his Commiſſion, he ſoon can reach forth his Hand, arreſt us, and ſtop our further Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. <hi>Man in the Vigour and Prime of his years,</hi> Phancies himſelf in the midſt of a vaſt Plain; he looks behind him, and numbers all the weary Steps of Life he has already taken, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades himſelf that Death muſt alſo meaſure the ſame ſpace of years in his Purſuit, before he can o'retake Him; then turning his Eyes before, he ſees a <hi>boundleſs Tract,</hi> an indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:94860:45"/> ſet of years; being thus deluded by the Inchanted Proſpect, he ruſhes on, and bids defiance to pale languid death, imagining he ſees him lagging afar off, at the firſt entrance of all the <hi>wide-ſtretch'd Waſte,</hi> whereas the nimble <hi>Skeleton</hi> is as far advanc'd as he, only keeps out of ſight, and will never be ſeen till the very moment he gives the fatal ſtroke. To whatſoever <hi rend="blackletterType">Light</hi> Mans turn his Face, death like his <hi>Shadow,</hi> whips behind Him ſtill, and is at his Back, but ne're will <hi rend="blackletterType">Face him, till the lateſt Gaſp.</hi> And he that can ſtoutly bear his Looks for that one Moment, ſhall never ſee him more to all Eternity. 'Tis but the Fear of this one Moments Pain, that makes our Lives ſo uneaſie all along. And I am really aſham'd of this incorrigible Folly of Mortals, who ſpend ſo many years in pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſquiſitions how to protract the Pain of <hi>one poor moment,</hi> and undergo ten times more Labour to eſcape it, than they can poſſibly feel in undergoing it. I admire the Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Indian Wives,</hi> who in contempt of Death, ſcorn to ſurvive their Husband's <hi>Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Pile, but with chaſte Zeal, and an undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Courage, throw themſelves into the Flames, as if they were then going to the Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Bed. Certainly they calculate aright, who reckon the Day of our Death, the Day of our Nativity, ſince we are then Born to the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Immortal Life. For this Reaſon I honour the Memory of <hi>Ludovicus Carteſius</hi> the <hi>Paduan</hi> Lawyer, who in his Laſt Will and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:94860:45"/> Teſtament ordered, that no ſad Funeral Rites ſhould be obſerv'd for Him, but that His Corps ſhould be attended with <hi>Muſick and Joy</hi> to the Grave, and as if it were the Day of his Eſpouſals, he commanded that Twelve Suits of Gay Apparel ſhould be provided inſtead of Mourning for an equal number of Virgins, who ſhould uſher his Body to the Church.</p>
            <p>It will not, I hope, be an unpardonable Tranſition, if I <hi>ſtart back</hi> from the melancholy Horrours of <hi>Death,</hi> to the innocent Comforts of <hi>Humane Life,</hi> and from the Immortal Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of this <hi>Italian,</hi> paſs to the Mortal Emblem, the Rites of Matrimony, the Happineſs of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Society,</hi> and our Obligations to Women. 'Tis an uncourtly Vertue, which admits of no Proſelytes but Men devoted to Coelibacy, and he is a Reproach to his Parents, who ſhuns the Entertainments of Hymen, the bliſsful Amours of the Fair Sex, without which he himſelf had not gain'd ſo much as the Poſt of a <hi>Cypher,</hi> in the Numeration of Mankind, though he now makes a Figure too much in Natures Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick, ſince he wou'd put a ſtop to the Rule of <hi>Multiplication.</hi> He is worſe than <hi>Numa Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius,</hi> who appointed but a ſet number of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and thoſe were free to Marry, after they had guarded the Sacred Fires, the Term of four years: VVhereas if his moroſe Example were follow'd, all VVomen ſhould turn <hi>Veſtals</hi> againſt their wills, and be conſecrated to a <hi>peeviſh Virginity</hi> during their Lives. I wonder at the unnatural Phancy of ſuch as could wiſh
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:94860:46"/> we might procreate like Trees, as if they were <hi>aſham'd of the Act,</hi> without which they had never been capable of ſuch an extravagant Thought, or like <hi>Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> would correct the Inſtitutions of Heaven, and ſay, Had they been preſent with God, when he commanded <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> to encreaſe and multiply, they would have propos'd a bette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> method for Generation. Certainly he that Created us, and has riveted the <hi>Love of Women</hi> in the very Center of our Natures, never gave us thoſe paſſionate Deſires to be our incurable Torment, but only as Spurs to our Wit and Vertue, that by the Dexterity of the One and the Integrity of the Other, we might Merit and Gain the <hi>Darling Object</hi> which ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate our Earthly Happineſs.</p>
            <p>I do not patronize the Smoke of thoſe <hi>Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill-Paſſions,</hi> who only court the Poſſeſſions of an Heireſs, and fall in Love with her Money. <hi>This is to make a Market of Women,</hi> and proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the Nobleſt Affection of our Souls to the ſordid Ends of Avarice. Neither do I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the ſofter Aims of thoſe, who are wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only to the <hi>Charming Lineaments</hi> of a Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Face, a clear Sk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, or a well ſhap'd Body. 'Tis only the Vertue, Diſcretion, and <hi>good Humour</hi> of a Woman could ever captivate me, and I am bleſs'd in a Mate who has her ſhare both of theſe and the other exteriour Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>I hate the Cynical Flout of thoſe who can afford Women no better Title than <hi>Neceſſary
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:94860:46"/> Evils,</hi> and the lewd Poetical Licence of Him who made this Anagram, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor &amp; Orcus — idem.</hi> That Oratour whiſper'd the <hi>Doctrine of Devils,</hi> who ſaid, Were it not for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Women, Angels would come down and dwell among us. I rather think, were it not for ſuch ill natur'd Fellows as he, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men themſelves would prove Angels</p>
            <p>'Tis an ungrateful Return, thus to abuſe that <hi>Gentle Sex, who are the Moulds in which all the Race of</hi> Adam <hi>are caſt:</hi> As if they deſerv'd no better Treatment at our Hands, than we uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally give to Saffron Bags and Verde Bottles, which are thrown into a Corner, when the Wine and Spice are taken out of them. The Pagan Poet was little better than a Murderer, who allow'd but two good Hours to a VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nam in Thalamo, alteram in Tumulo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For my Part, I ſhould eſteem the VVorld but a <hi>Deſert,</hi> were it not for the Society of the <hi>Fair Sex;</hi> and the moſt Poliſhed Part of Mankind wou'd appear but like Hermits in Maſquerade, or a kind of <hi>Civilized Satyrs,</hi> ſo imperfect and unaccompliſh'd is our Virility, without the Reunion of our <hi>loſt Rib,</hi> that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial and Integral Part of our Selves. Thoſe who are thus disjoynted from VVomen, ſeem to inherit <hi>Adam's Dreams,</hi> out of which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can awake them, but the Embraces of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:94860:47"/> their own living Image, the Fair Traduct of the firſt Metamorphoſis in the VVorld, <hi>the Bone converted into Fleſh.</hi> They are always in Slumbers and Trances, ever ſeparated from themſelves, in <hi>a wild Purſuit</hi> of an intolerab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Loſs, nor can any thing fix their Volatile De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, but the powerful Magnetiſm of ſome Charming <hi>Daughter of Eve.</hi> Theſe are the Centers of all our Deſires and VViſhes, the true <hi>Pandoras</hi> that alone can ſatisfie our longing Appetites, and fill us with <hi>Gifts and Bleſſings, in them we live before we breathe,</hi> and when we have taſted the <hi>Vital Air,</hi> 'tis but to die an amorous Death, that we may live more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly in them again. <hi>They are the Guardians of our Infancy, the Life and Soul of our Youth, the Companions of our Riper Years, and the Cheriſhers of our Old Age.</hi> From the Cradle to the Tomb, we are wrapt in a Circle of Obligations to them for their Love and good Offices. And he is a Monſter in Nature who returns them not the Careſſes of an <hi>Innocent</hi> Affection, the Spotleſs Sallies of Vertue and Gratitude. <hi>Loue is the Soul of the World,</hi> the Vital Prop of the Elements, 'tis the Cement of Humane Society, the ſtrongeſt Fence of Nature. Earth would be a Hell without it, neither can there be any Heaven where this is abſent.</p>
            <p>Yet I am no <hi>Advocate for thoſe general Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> who not content to let this active Paſſion run within the lawful Channel of chaſt Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, ſwell it up with irregular Tides, and wanton Flouds of Luſt, till it waſh away the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:94860:47"/> Banks of Reaſon and Morality, find out new Paſſages and Rivulets, encroaching on other Mens Poſſeſſions, or at leaſt dilating on the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral waſte of the weaker Sex, who ought to be as Gardens enclos'd, or holy Ground not to be prophan'd by the Acceſs of every bold Intruder.</p>
            <p>I approve not the Inceſtuous Mixtures of the <hi>Chineſe</hi> where the Brother Marries the Siſter, or next a-kin; nor the Senſual Latitude of the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> who allow every Man four VVives, and as many Concubines as he can maintain. But above all I deteſt the wild and Brutal Liberty of that <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> who in his Idea of Humane Happineſs, conceiv'd a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous Copulation <hi>ad Libitum</hi> to be a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ingredient of our Bliſs.</p>
            <p>On the Other ſide, My Regards to that <hi>Sex</hi> are not circumſcrib'd within ſuch narrow Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, as to exclude any from our Converſation and Friendſhip, that by any warrantable Title can lay a Juſt Claim to it; I wou'd have our Commerce with Females <hi>as General</hi> as is their Number that deſerve it, whoſe Knowledge and Vertue will be a ſufficient ſecurity from <hi>criminal Familiarities,</hi> and from the Scandals of the World. There are among that Sex as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men, Good and Bad, Vertuous and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and a Prudent Man will ſo level his Cho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, as not to ſtain his Reputation, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard his Integrity. 'Tis no ſmall Point of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, I own, to <hi>regulate our Friendſhips with Women,</hi> and to walk evenly on the Borders
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:94860:48"/> and very <hi>Ridge of a Paſſion,</hi> whoſe next Step i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Precipice of Flames not kindled from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Altar of Vertue. However, 'tis not impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>conſerve Innocency, on the Frontiers of Vic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> There is no Difference of Sex among Souls,</hi> and Maſculine Spirit may inhabit a Womans Bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> It is diſingenuous to rob Vertue of the Adva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages it receives from Beauty, which make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> appear like Diamonds enchac'd in Gold, a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> gives it a greater Luſtre. <hi>Reaſon it ſelf will <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pear more Eloquent in the Mouth of a fair Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than in that of the moſt Florid Oratour:</hi> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there are no Figures in all the Syſtem of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torick ſo moving and forcible as the <hi>peculia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Graces of that Sex.</hi> I am of Opinion that Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can boaſt of no Endowments of the Mind which Women poſſeſs not in as great, if not a greater Eminency. There have been <hi>Muſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as well as Amazons,</hi> and no Age or Nation bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> has produced ſome Females Renowned for their Wiſdom or Vertue. Which makes me conclude that the Converſation of Women is no leſs uſeful than pleaſant, and that the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which attend their Friendſhips and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, are recompenſed by vaſt Advantages.</p>
            <p>But whatever may be adduced againſt the <hi>Friendſhips</hi> we contract with Women, there is not in all the <hi>Magazine</hi> of <hi>Detraction</hi> any Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon of Proof againſt the mutual Intimacies of our <hi>own Sex, the generous Endearments of Souls truely Maſculine and Vertuous, united by Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies and Magnets whoſe Root is in Heaven.</hi> No Panegyricks can reach the Worth of theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:94860:48"/> Engagements, ſince they admit not of any Mediocrity, but derive their <hi>Value only from their Exceſs.</hi> I have been always ſlow and cautious in contracting Amities, leſt I ſhould run the Riſque of his Miſtake, who while he thought he had an Angel by the Hand, held the Devil by the Foot: But where I have once <hi>pitch'd</hi> my Affection, I love without Reſerve or Rule. I never entertain without ſuſpicion the warm Profeſſions of Love, which ſome Men are apt to make at firſt ſight. Such <hi>Muſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room-Friendſhips</hi> have no deep Root, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt commonly wither as ſoon as they are form'd. Yet I deny not, but that there are ſome <hi>ſecret Marks</hi> and Signatures which Souls ordain'd for Love and Friendſhip can read in each other at a Glance, by which that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Paſſion is excited, that afterwards diſplays it ſelf in more apparent Characters. This is the <hi>ſilent Language</hi> of Platonick Love, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Eye ſupplies the Office of the Tongue; <hi>'tis the Rhetorick of Amorous Spirits</hi> wherein they make their Court without a Word. There are ſome laſting Friendſhips which owe their Birth to ſuch an Interview, but their Growth and Faſtneſs proceeds from other Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, being cheriſh'd by frequent Converſation, repeated good Offices, and an inviolate Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which are the only proper and ſubſtantial Aliment of Love. 'Tis impoſſible to fix a durable Friendſhip, where-ever we place a <hi>Tranſient Inclination,</hi> becauſe of the inſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Neceſſities which divide particular Men
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:94860:49"/> from each Others Commerce or Knowledge after they have begun to Love. In the Orb of this Life Men are like the Planets, which now and then caſt friendly Aſpects on each other <hi>en Paſſant:</hi> But following the Motio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Greater Sphere of Providence, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are again ſeparated, their Influences diſſolv'd and new Amours commenc'd. But I would have my Friendſhip, reſemble the <hi>Fixed Sta<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and Conſtellations, who in the Eternal Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution never part Company or Intereſts.</p>
            <p>I have ever look'd on thoſe Men to be bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>one ſtep differenc'd from Beaſts,</hi> whoſe Love is confined only to their own Families or Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Such a narrow Affection deſerves not to be rank'd in the <hi>Praedicament of Humanity.</hi> My Love is communicative it makes a large Progreſs, and extends it ſelf to Strangers, it takes in Men of different Humours and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions, Cuſtoms and Languages, it refuſes none that have the <hi>Face of Men,</hi> but with wide-open'd Arms embraces all that bear the ſtamp of Humane Nature. And I have this <hi>peculiar in my Temper,</hi> that I find not the leaſt Reluctancy in loving and doing Good to my <hi>Enemies.</hi> That which coſts others ſo much La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Toil to perſwade themſelves to, is to me as familiar and eaſie, as to laugh at a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Object, and I eſteem it not ſo proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Vertue in my Self, as a Gift of Nature, the Effect of my Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>Yet I cannot pretend to ſuch an <hi>univerſaliz'd Spirit,</hi> as to be without my <hi>Antipathies.</hi> I
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:94860:49"/> eſteem Hatred to be as neceſſary and allowable a Paſſion as Love, provided it be exercis'd on its proper Objects, ſince as the One faſtens us to thoſe Things which procure our Happineſs, ſo the Other ſnatches us from what would be the Cauſe of our Miſery. I obſerve, that theſe <hi>contrary Faculties</hi> are inherent in all Creatures, neither could the Creation ſubſiſt, were it not for the Diſcords as well as the Agreements of the Elements. The whole Univerſe ſubſiſts by the <hi>Oppoſition of its Parts,</hi> and the Epitome of it, our Microcoſm is preſerv'd by its <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine</hi> Diviſions. So that I cannot apprehend a more immediate Way for the Supreme Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect to overthrow his Works, than by dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing that <hi>Nepenthe</hi> through the Elements, which ſhould compoſe their Quarrels, for they wou'd no ſooner ceaſe to hate their <hi>Contraries,</hi> but they wou'd alſo deſiſt from loving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and having thus loſt the Cement which faſtens them together in this exquiſite Order, they muſt neceſſarily return to their Primitive Chaos out of which they were extracted.</p>
            <p>However I will not from theſe <hi>innocent Feuds of inanimate Creatures</hi> draw Arguments to countenance in my ſelf a Hatred which is Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, being aſſured that among thoſe <hi>various Averſions</hi> which moleſt the Quiet of Men, there is hardly one which is not againſt Reaſon or Morality. Every Creature bears in its Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence the ſtamp of Infinite Goodneſs; and 'twere groſs Impiety to calumniate any of thoſe Works, on which God Himſelf has beſtow'd
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:94860:50"/> an <hi>univerſal Panegyrick,</hi> when he pronounc'd them all to be Good. They are all lovely in their Order, and thoſe which our Squeamiſh Phancies eſteem the moſt odious, have Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which claim our Love and Admiration. Thoſe <hi>venemous Creatures</hi> which we ſhun as the inveterate Enemies of our Race, deſerve ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Careſſes inſtead of our Spight, ſince the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they afford us, equals the Hurt we receive from them, and the moſt Efficacious Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are ſometimes compounded of the <hi>fierceſt Poyſons.</hi> In ſtrict ſpeaking, the <hi>Devils</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are not the Object of my Hatred, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Eſſence, though they are ſo by the Malice of their Will. They ſtill retain their <hi>Natural Perfections,</hi> and the Goodneſs of their Eſſence remains the ſame as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Fall. Their Vigour, Beauty, and Intellectual Accompliſhments, have ſuffered no Detriment from the Depravedneſs of their Affections, but remain untouch'd, as when they <hi>ſhone among the Hierarchies above.</hi> And though God deteſts and puniſhes them for their Crimes, yet he Himſelf loves and <hi>conſerves their Eſſence.</hi> There is Nothing therefore in <hi>Heaven, Earth or Hell</hi> but <hi rend="blackletterType">Sin</hi> that deſerves our Hatred; with all things elſe we may be enamour'd; and we ought to hate this Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſo much the more, in that by diſordering our Natures, it has planted in us thoſe <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathies</hi> and Averſions which make us peeviſh at the Works of God, and hate thoſe Things which we ought to love.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:94860:50"/>
            <p>But among all the <hi>Species of Hatred,</hi> I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at that which is exercis'd againſt our own Race, becauſe I find none ſo violent, none ſo inexorable as one Man againſt another. They are not content with the moſt furious Sallies of this Paſſion during their Lives, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate the Height of their Malice, they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly involve themſelves in Death. With <hi>Atreus</hi> they take Delight in their own Ruine, provided <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> may be cruſh'd in it too. Nay this Paſſion is <hi>Immortal,</hi> and deſcends into the very Grave. The Antipathies of <hi>Eteocles</hi> and <hi>Polenius</hi> were tranſlated to the other World, their Hatred <hi>ſurviv d their Breath,</hi> it liv'd in their Aſhes, and wou'd not ſuffer their divided Flames to mix in the ſame Funeral Pile. Above all I abhor the <hi>Italians</hi> inſlexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cruelty, who bequeath their Hatred as an Inheritance to their Children, adjuring them to Eternal Enmity, with Curſes on ſuch of their Off-ſpring as ſhall ever make Peace with their Foes.</p>
            <p>I quarrel not with that <hi>Logick,</hi> by which we call a Toad venemous. 'Twou'd prove but a thin <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> that ſhou'd impoſe on us the Safety of the Experiment; and I doubt our beſt <hi>Metaphyſicks</hi> wou'd make but a weak An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt the Force of its Poyſon. I am not fond of <hi>quibbling</hi> my ſelf into ſo dangerous an Abſurdity under the Protection of a refin'd Theory, whoſe Practice wou'd convince me of a fooliſh Madneſs, and that I were neither good Philoſopher nor Divine. Yet I cannot
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:94860:51"/> ſay I hate even this Creature which is become the Proverb of Humane Hatred: For as much as it carries with it, in its Life and Motion, the Character and Impreſſion of a <hi>Divine Artificer</hi> eſpecially for this reaſon, that we have no ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to believe it ever ſinned, and conſequently thereupon maintains and performs the end and deſign of its Creation, which tho' it be in a lower Sphere, has this Prerogative beyond Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; that it never yet tranſgreſs'd the Rules, nor violated the Laws of its Maker. Nor can I imagine whence our Reflections upon ſuch Creatures ſhould ariſe, but from a miſtaken Knowledge of our ſelves, and a perfect Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Nature of all things beſide. 'Tis under the Prejudice of Education, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Influence of Cuſtom that we labour, and to which we owe the greateſt and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected Errors of our Life. Have not ſome Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple liv'd upon that, and deliciouſly too, that is another Man's Poyſon? Did not <hi>Mithridates</hi> take Poyſon till the ſtrongeſt Confection of that kind would not do his buſineſs when he wanted it? 'Tis to that we are to aſcribe the Miſchiefs of Humane Life. For if we could once forſake the <hi>falſe Guide</hi> we have been us'd to, and conſult our own Reaſon there's nothing would ſeem ſtrange to us, nothing uneaſie, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dreadful. Therefore after I have a little Deſcanted upon this Subject, in order to Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie our Judgments and Reform our Practices, I ſhall croſs the Cudgels, and end this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:94860:51"/>
            <p>It is impoſſible fully to ſet forth the large Dominion and uncontroulable Power of <hi>Cuſtom</hi> and common <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage,</hi> together with the vaſt and long <hi>Series</hi> of <hi>Difficulties and Miſtakes</hi> we lye lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and expos'd unto upon that account. 'Tis the Maſter of the Mint, and <hi>Coins Words and Names</hi> for things according to its own pleaſure, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not at all expreſſive of the Nature of the thing intended; which have no further ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation than what they obtain by repeated uſe and frequency. We know very well that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in its own Nature is <hi>accidental,</hi> and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Supreme Author all things are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and Deſigned; but in Reference to us whoſe <hi>purblind Reaſon</hi> can reach no deeper than the Outſide, whoſe Sight is not ſharp enough to Dive and Penetrate into the Cauſes of things, many things prove fortuitous. When Events ſtrange and unexpected fall out, ſuch as we had not the leaſt apprehenſion or ſuſpicion of before-hand, we call it <hi>Chance and Accident.</hi> But the Miſery is we Terminate there, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver look to the hand that Order'd it. We at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute that to <hi>Fortune</hi> which is the Effect of a Wiſe and Skilful <hi>Agent.</hi> When our Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are baulk'd, and our Aims fruſtrated, we cry 'twas done by chance and think that's all. Whereas we ought to conſider that God often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times delights to make our <hi>Wiſdom Fooliſhneſs,</hi> and thereby gives us caution not to truſt our own Foreſight; ſince the Events of all things are in his Power and at his Diſpoſal. He will be <hi>Ey'd in his Providence,</hi> and make Men know
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:94860:52"/> that the Succeſs of all their Undertakings is at his Diſcretion. That he is the Sole Governor of the World: That he will be ſought unto for his Bleſſing, and that we muſt wait his Pleaſure and aſcribe the Glory of all to Him But this ought not to Encourage us in a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine and Slothful Negligence; That becauſe God does all things according to the Good Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Will, we have nothing to do, but expect he ſhou'd bring things about for Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and Satisfaction. For tho' <hi>Grace</hi> loves to <hi>magnifie</hi> it ſelf in the <hi>Weak,</hi> and exerts its Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy in mean and contemptible Subjects, yet that's no Ground for us to ſtand <hi>Idle,</hi> or ſit <hi>whining</hi> and bewailing our Misfortunes, and think <hi>God</hi> ſhou'd bear our burden himſelf. No, theſe Remarkable Efforts of the <hi>Divine</hi> Power are to Encourage our Stedfaſtneſs, and confirm us in the belief of its undoubted Preſence, when our Deſigns and Endeavours are conformable. It is Impertinent and Ridiculous to expect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief from others, when we are wholly unactive to procure it our ſelves. We ought to make uſe of the beſt Means he affords us, and then Reſigning our ſelves up to him attend the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. If it be according to our Deſires we muſt gratefully acknowledge, and thank him for it: If contrary, we muſt in all Humility ſubmit, confeſſing his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> infinitely to exceed <hi>ours,</hi> and that he knows what is better for us than we our ſelves This is what <hi>Divinity</hi> teaches us, and cou'd we be inſtructed by it, might great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advance our Peace and Tranquillity in this World.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:94860:52"/>
            <p>This is a ſtrain of Prudence, I know, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind can hardly be Skrew'd up to. The Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Humane Nature is ſuch, that every Shock of unexpected Adverſity makes it ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. VVe are ready to turn <hi>Recreants,</hi> and yield the day to every puny Evil, that unlook'd for attacks us. 'Tis well if we can ſupport <hi>our Spirits</hi> and preſerve our Courage againſt a fore-ſeen Danger; but to be <hi>ſurpriz'd</hi> by a Misfortune is to be <hi>Overcome.</hi> I am of Opinion the <hi>Combat</hi> would not be Difficult, nor the <hi>Victory</hi> Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, were we but better acquainted with <hi>our ſelves;</hi> and knew our own ſtrength, and how to apply our ſelves to the <hi>Work.</hi> Some torment themſelves with <hi>Diſtracting</hi> Apprehenſions afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and <hi>doubly</hi> poſſeſs their Miſery in <hi>Reality</hi> and <hi>Fancy.</hi> Others immediately ſink under the Weight as ſoon as they feel it on their <hi>Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> Others fly out into <hi>Deſpair,</hi> as if the World were at an End, and they were <hi>never</hi> to ſee a good Day again. For my part, as I cannot alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether boaſt of <hi>Inſenſibility,</hi> under my afflictions at <hi>preſent;</hi> ſo neither can I complain of being too <hi>Apprehenſive</hi> of them at <hi>diſtance.</hi> I can ſee the <hi>Cloud</hi> gathering without much <hi>Consternation,</hi> and comfort my ſelf with this, that perhaps ſome Wind or other may blow it away, or I am not Infallibly ſure it ſhall break on my Head. I ſhall have enough of it whenever it comes and do not ſo much provide to <hi>avoid</hi> it, as conſider of what Importance it may be whether I <hi>eſcape</hi> it or no. Perhaps 'tis my <hi>Fault,</hi> but I am willing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge it. I have no other Means. I can conſider
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:94860:53"/> it without too <hi>much concern.</hi> I approach it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Horror.</hi> I bring it home to <hi>my ſelf,</hi> and treat with it as <hi>Preſent,</hi> when perhaps it may never come to paſs I Inure my ſelf to it, and harden my ſelf in it, by which means it becomes familiar to me, That when it overtakes me I claim <hi>acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> with it. This <hi>dulls</hi> the Edge, and <hi>blunts</hi> the Sting of an Affliction; which otherwiſe it may be I ſhould never be able to <hi>ſustain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us Examine <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and ſee what Arms ſhe can furniſh us with for our Defence, againſt theſe Violent Aſſaults. <hi>She</hi> would in a great meaſure do our Buſineſs for us, could we take <hi>her</hi> advice, and were there not <hi>private</hi> Enemies <hi>within,</hi> that compel us to Surrender before we try our Strength. If our <hi>Paſſions</hi> were Diſarmed and Subdued, and brought into Obedience to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> we might maintain our Ground with leſs Difficulty, and <hi>bid</hi> Defiance to <hi>Fortune.</hi> This ought to be the <hi>Subject</hi> of our Courage. In this we ſhall appear more than <hi>Conquerors.</hi> Let us ſtop theſe <hi>beginnings</hi> and our Buſineſs is ſoon done. Nothing in Nature can be more Tumultuous and Irregular than our own Paſſions. And with what Face can any Man pretend to withſtand the ſudden and violent attempts of <hi>Fortune,</hi> that has no Guard againſt the inward and unruly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his own <hi>Soul?</hi> Whither do we ſee ſome People hurried, by the precipituous Streams of <hi>Anger, Love, Hatred,</hi> &amp;c. even upon a bare Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and Jealouſie, without the leaſt Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Cauſe or Motive? I have ſeen the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental breaking of a <hi>Glaſs,</hi> the loſs of a <hi>Groat,</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:94860:53"/> tranſport ſome to ſuch a <hi>Degree,</hi> that they could hardly Compoſe and Recover themſelves for <hi>ſix</hi> hours after. They fall foul upon all without Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, all Company muſt be Diſturb'd where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they come, 'tis impoſſible to give a calm uninterrupted anſwer to any thing that is ask'd them. They Stamp, Stare, Burn, Rave, Fret, Roar, as if the <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Judgment</hi> was at hand, and they were a going <hi>Quick</hi> to <hi>Pluto.</hi> Wherefore do you wring your Hands? Why are thoſe Tears? Why look you ſo Diſcontented? You have loſt your beſt <hi>Friend.</hi> A dear Relation. You are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid you ſhall be <hi>Poor.</hi> The <hi>Wheel</hi> is come upon you. You cannot ſee how your Eſtate will hold out, and know not how to Live when that is gone. <hi>Poor Wretch!</hi> The plain truth is you have loſt your Reaſon. What is become of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, your Faith, your Confidence? Is this the upſhot of all your talk of relying on Providence, of truſting God? Do you not <hi>Belye</hi> your ſelves? Is he not Able? Is he not Willing? Why are you not <hi>Calm?</hi> Why are you not <hi>Quiet?</hi> They may talk as long as they pleaſe, but it muſt be ſomewhat more than a few fine Words, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therical Expreſſions, that muſt convince me of the ſincerity of their Profeſſion, who Diſtruſt Providence upon every ſlender occaſion. <hi>Are not theſe brave men, think you? Grace</hi> delights to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company a Vigorous and Active Soul, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it out to perform Atchievements beyond its own ſtrength and above its hopes, but unleſs our <hi>Endeavours</hi> comport with our <hi>Words,</hi> Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence diſdains us as unworthy of his Care. What
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:94860:54"/> does that Souldier deſerve that brags of ſingly Conquering whole <hi>Armies,</hi> and turns his <hi>Back</hi> at the firſt Charge; nay, runs away perhaps before the Enemy is in view, thro' a ſlaviſh deſpair of his own ability to reſiſt? <hi>Our whole Life is a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</hi> We have many Adverſaries to Encounter. Some <hi>face</hi> us in the <hi>open</hi> Field, and give us leiſure to prepare, and require a ſixt and determinate reſolution to oppoſe them. Some ſurprize us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Hedge</hi> and the Ditch, as they ſay, and expect we ſhould be perpetually armed and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Watch.</hi> Theſe are <hi>Trials</hi> ſent on purpoſe to evidence our Conſtancy, and if we bear up manfully, our Courage ſhall be <hi>ſeconded</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with an <hi>Almighty</hi> aſſiſtance. Yet it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Obſervation, that none are more apt to repine, than ſuch whoſe <hi>Tongues</hi> can run nimbly in <hi>matters</hi> of this nature.</p>
            <p>To what purpoſe then ſhou'd we torment our ſelves and others? And ſeeing we are <hi>unable</hi> to govern our ſelves or our Affairs, why do we not deliver up our ſelves to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</hi> of him who Governs the VVorld? VVhy do we mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our Souls and Bodies when our vain Imaginations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſucceſsleſs and ineffectual? Since there is a VViſe and Intelligent Moderator, who will bring things about accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Methods of his own <hi>ſuperlative</hi> VViſdom, in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Humane <hi>Craft</hi> and Policy. VVe may lay the <hi>Scheme</hi> of our Affairs as rationally as we can deviſe, and back it with our utmoſt power and diligence, and then we have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied our <hi>Office</hi> and done our Duty for in ſpite of all, the <hi>Iſſue</hi> and Reſult of all muſt finally and arbitrarily depend upon the abſolute Will and Pleaſure of another.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded <hi>Cuſtom</hi> and <hi>Example,</hi> lead us into more Errors and Miſtakes than any thing elſe beſide. I find we ſubmit to them with great eaſe and little reluctance. Nay, and think our ſelves very excuſable in all the <hi>ſlips</hi> we make when we follow that <hi>Guide.</hi> Our very Diſpoſitions, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, and natural Inclinations are ſubdued by them. And
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:94860:54"/> in many things drawn to a compliance, even againſt their own <hi>Biaſs.</hi> They <hi>Habituate</hi> us to Actions, however Ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Diſreliſhing at their firſt appearance, and aſſiſt us to perform them with <hi>Smoothneſs</hi> and <hi>Facility.</hi> I find the Path <hi>rugged</hi> when I am out of my uſual <hi>way,</hi> and we are content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>jogg</hi> on, quietly in a <hi>wrong</hi> Road, rather than put our ſelves to the Trouble of finding out the <hi>right.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Brutiſh</hi> and Unmanly not to examine what we do, and to be able to give no better account of our Actions, than that it is the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of the <hi>Place.</hi> To what purpoſe ſerve our rational and diſcerning Faculties, if we ſuſpend their Exerciſe, and not ſuffer them to have their <hi>Play</hi> in their natural and proper <hi>Velitations?</hi> Why ſhou'd we debaſe our own Judgments by a ſlaviſh ſubmiſſion to common uſage. I then fruſtrate the end of my Being, for one of the main buſineſſes I have <hi>here</hi> is to acquire the <hi>knowledge of my ſelf.</hi> And 'tis for my own Actions I ſhall be immediately accountable, and not thoſe of other men. <hi>Example,</hi> I confeſs, may be of great uſe, but then it muſt be manag'd according to <hi>diſcretion.</hi> It may ſerve as a <hi>Caution</hi> but never as a <hi>Rule:</hi> It may be admitted into <hi>Council,</hi> but not entruſted with the <hi>Government.</hi> It may prove an Excellent <hi>Monitor,</hi> but a very wretched <hi>Dictator.</hi> Nor when thus qualified and circumſcribed can it be of any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to us, without a previous knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of our ſelves. 'Tis the <hi>VViſe man</hi> only, that knows his own ſtrength, that ſhall uſe it with ſucceſs. And as ſuch an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e has leſs need of it; ſo he ſhall be further removed from it; Inſinuating and Uſurping <hi>Dominion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wou'd therefore begin firſt with <hi>my ſelf,</hi> ranſack my own Soul, and exactly know its frame and conſtitution. I wou'd <hi>muſter</hi> my own forces firſt, and <hi>dive</hi> into the truth of things, and put my Underſtanding upon the Exerciſe of its Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and give my Judgment its full <hi>ſwing.</hi> Truth ſhall be the Subject of my <hi>Diſquiſition,</hi> and the End of my <hi>Enquiry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we look into the <hi>behaviour</hi> and practice of moſt men, we ſhall find <hi>Fancy</hi> to have the <hi>Aſcendant</hi> over them. The <hi>Dread</hi> of not ſucceeding ſhakes their <hi>Reſolutions.</hi> They are <hi>Timorous</hi> and <hi>Inconſtant</hi> becauſe they neither know <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> nor what they wou'd be at. Every unſuſpected Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſcares them out of their Wits. They create <hi>Monſters</hi> in their own <hi>Brains,</hi> and ſuppoſing them above their ſtrength
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:94860:55"/> to reſiſt, they <hi>ſlaviſhly</hi> reſign the little Reaſon they wou'd ſeem to be <hi>Maſters</hi> of to every <hi>uncommon</hi> Evil, not knowing how to withſtand or avoid it. It behoves me then to Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the tendency of my own Deſires, and ſee whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing <hi>Subſtantial</hi> hath affected my mind. Hath any man met with any thing that gives him a full and compleat ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction? Or does he not find his Paſſions and Appetite to encreaſe upon him, and require ſomewhat more even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the very Poſſeſſion and Enjoyments of their Objects? We penetrate no deeper than the <hi>Surface,</hi> and acquieſce in a <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial</hi> Glance. We ought therefore to come out of the <hi>Dark,</hi> that we may ſee to walk in the <hi>Light.</hi> We muſt <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learn,</hi> what we <hi>think</hi> we know, to be taught what we <hi>ought</hi> to know. <hi>The firſt advance towards Wiſdom is to renounce our Folly.</hi> Our Minds can never be filled with ſound and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Knowledge, till they are firſt Diſpoſſeſt of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices.</p>
            <p>I hate to hear People cry out, Why cannot I do <hi>thus</hi> and <hi>thus?</hi> Why cannot I manage an Affair like this or that man? I'le tell you, becauſe you are a Fool, and do not <hi>know your ſelf:</hi> Becauſe you cannot be contented as you are. Uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Diſſatisfaction under a Mans <hi>preſent</hi> condition, is an aſſur'd and manifeſt proof he would carry himſelf as <hi>unhandſomly</hi> in <hi>another.</hi> Nature and Providence hath deſign'd every man his <hi>Task,</hi> and that which is moſt <hi>ſuitable</hi> to him. He that cannot <hi>Govern</hi> a <hi>Skuller</hi> would make an improper <hi>Commander</hi> of a Man of <hi>War.</hi> It would, I profeſs. make a Man laugh till he expires, to come into a <hi>Coffee-houſe,</hi> and behold a <hi>Pack</hi> of <hi>Cits</hi> prating of <hi>Politicks</hi> and State Matters, as if they were all <hi>Matchiavels</hi> and <hi>Mazarins.</hi> Had I been the <hi>King, ſays one,</hi> that has not Wit enough to commend him for a <hi>Rat-catcher,</hi> I wou'd have done <hi>Thus.</hi> Had I been in Council cries another, I wou'd never have adviſed <hi>That. Ye doating Coxcombs!</hi> Why don't ye Regulate your <hi>Families</hi> VVhy do you ſuffer your <hi>VVives</hi> to wear the <hi>Breeches</hi> VVhy do your <hi>Daughters</hi> run away with the <hi>Bullies</hi> And your <hi>Prentices</hi> get to Bed to their <hi>Miſtreſſes</hi> Amend your ſelves firſt, Correct your <hi>Domeſtick</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancies, <hi>Exemplifie your Prudence</hi> in Rectifying your private Affairs. Deal faithfully in your Trades, and become honeſt Men, and then you ſhall have leave to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:94860:55"/> prate. I have often conſidered with my ſelf, what ſhould be the reaſon Men are ſo often diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed of their Ends, and baulk'd in their Hopes? They undertake more than they can anſwer for, and by a ridiculous preſumption, enter upon Buſineſs they can never accompliſh. It is Ignorance that is the ground of all our Miſcarriages, and <hi>Pride</hi> puts us upon Attempts too weighty for our <hi>Shoulders.</hi> They are <hi>Twin-Siſters,</hi> and the latter is a Natural Companion of the former. We have every one of us within our own proper <hi>Sphere,</hi> more work cut out than we know well how to affect: Which one Conſideration, could it but duely take place, wou'd be of force enough to diſcourage us from loading our Shoulders with unneceſſary Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</p>
            <p>I am confident nothing more betrays the <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Infirmity</hi> of Humane Nature, than <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience</hi> under our preſent Circumſtances, and a buſie Curioſity of prying into the Affairs of other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 'Tis the Employment of a weak under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and a Soul wholly unacquainted with it ſelf, to be impetuouſly hurried with a deſire after things altogether beyond our proper Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. Surely Nature hath better provided for us, than we can for our ſelves; and did we but <hi>Regularly</hi> follow her Dictates, we ſhould not be ſo often compell'd to our ſhifts. But the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief is, we are too much prone to <hi>Admire</hi> every thing we do not poſſeſs. A <hi>Vanity intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable!</hi> Which did it not ſhroud it ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Covert of <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> wou'd ſoon be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor'd
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:94860:56"/> and baniſh'd out of the World. B<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Common Practice</hi> is become its <hi>Advocate,</hi> and reſiſtibly pleads its defence in a vulgar <hi>Judicatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Should we not think a <hi>Neighbour crack'd</hi> on o<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſide of his Head, who would entertain us a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hour or two together, with an exact and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curate <hi>Deſcription</hi> of ſome Foreign Countre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when all the while he does not know the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to his own Pariſh Church? <hi>Prepoſterous mad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs!</hi> to pretend to know every thing, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet be totally Ignorant of our ſelves.</p>
            <p>It is enough already, that I have lived fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>others.</hi> Let me at laſt return home, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſomewhat for my ſelf. Time flies away, Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture decays, and I ſhall ſoon find my ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> moſt unfit for the Work, when I ſhall ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt in need of ſtrength to do it. To wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> purpoſe is it, we are ſo buſily concern'd i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Exotick Affairs,</hi> things neither conſiſte<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with our <hi>preſent</hi> Peace, nor conducive to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>future</hi> Happineſs?</p>
            <p>When I take a review, and give my min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leave (as ſhe would often do, did I not im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertinently divert her) to Recollect her ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thoughts, and make a ſerious Reflection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Employments</hi> and <hi>Enjoyments</hi> too of h<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> paſt life. Good God! how full of Vanit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Inquietude, and diſſatisfaction do they ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pear? As enforces from me a <hi>Subſcription</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this <hi>Fatal</hi> Truth; that it is I my ſelf tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have prevented my own happineſs, and by a ſenſeleſs Extravagance, and ſtupid Self-Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, undermined the Tranquility of a <hi>Life</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:94860:56"/> that might have been more <hi>Peaceable,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſequently more <hi>pleaſant,</hi> than the preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſpect of any Circumſtances now warrant me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o expect. I could now almoſt Hate, and Curſe my ſelf, as to my <hi>Folly,</hi> and <hi>Self-Love</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſelf, would juſtifie my Indignation. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is not the Way, and Prudence ſuggeſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nother Courſe. Let me therefore at leaſt preſerve what I enjoy, if I cannot Recover what I have loſt. Let the conſideration of what is paſt, awaken my diligence for the <hi>Future.</hi> We have been Fools, and who has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot? Let Wiſdome make amends and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el the <hi>Shame.</hi> I have learn'd at leaſt, this by the Bargain, to know my Diſtemper, which makes the Cure leſs difficult. There is ſomewhat of <hi>Good</hi> to be extracted from every thing: And Preſcriptions in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance contrary, have Eventually proved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Friendly</hi> to Nature.</p>
            <p>To do our own proper buſineſs, and to know <hi>our ſelves,</hi> is the only important Employment we have in this World. And he that can do the <hi>latier,</hi> will never be at a loſs in the <hi>former.</hi> He will avoid all ſuperfluous Undertakings. He can tell how to Reform the Extravagance of his Paſſions, and correct the Impetuoſity of an <hi>hot</hi> Nature. He will never be obliged to Proſecute the Concerns of <hi>Another,</hi> while any thing of his own lies on his Hands. Every thing he En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages in ſhall be brought to perfection; becauſe he attempts no more than he <hi>underſtands,</hi> and is able to Accompliſh. This Conſideration wou'd
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:94860:57"/> fix our Thoughts, reſtrain and bridle our D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſires, and limit our Fancies within their o<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Bounds.</p>
            <p>It has been my Obſervation ever ſince I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been acquainted in the World, That moſt M<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are <hi>ſtrays,</hi> they are guilty of a perpetual <hi>Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſs,</hi> and a <hi>Clauſum fregit</hi> may be charg'd upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us <hi>all.</hi> We ſee how fooliſh and impertine<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſoever Men ordinarily are, yet they obſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Decorum,</hi> and put a conſtraint upon their Word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Actions, when they are in the Company o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Perſons reputed <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Good:</hi> And an Af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>front put upon them before <hi>ſuch,</hi> will be more highly Reſented, than if they were all of their own <hi>Stamp</hi> and <hi>Rank.</hi> So ſhou'd we learn to be acquainted, and reverence our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and dare to think and ſpeak nothing in our own Preſence, we ſhould be aſhamed of before a <hi>Solomon</hi> or a <hi>Cato.</hi> Let us then for once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our own Maſters: Let us conſult our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and take advice of our <hi>Reaſon:</hi> 'Tis ſhe alone will inſtruct us, not only what we have to do, but alſo govern us in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Actions, with much leſs ſolicitude, and much more facility. The Soveraignty is her <hi>Due,</hi> our <hi>Paſſions</hi> are her <hi>Slaves,</hi> and ſhe ought to have the <hi>Principal,</hi> if not the <hi>only</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence in all our Attempts. Leave the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs wholly to her, and you ſhall find ſhe will render the Event at leaſt excuſable, let it be what it will.</p>
            <p>How vain is it thus to <hi>ſhun</hi> our ſelves, and follow the <hi>multitude!</hi> That Man muſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:94860:57"/> deſerve <hi>Bedla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who employs all his time in examining the Eſtates of others, and values him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for knowing the particular Concerns of the Nobleſt <hi>Families</hi> of the Nation, when yet he is a <hi>Stranger</hi> to what paſſes under his own <hi>Roof,</hi> and can never find leiſure to adjuſt his own <hi>private</hi> Accounts. For my part, I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of my ſelf, That little knowledge I have acquired of my own Temper, if ſo much as to let me know the neceſſity I have of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more. It is difficult for us to arrive at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tollerable Information of <hi>anothers</hi> Humour, and to give a juſt and regular Eſtimate of him; we muſt follow him cloſe, purſue all his Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Turnings, trace him through all his Variations, Forms, and Appearances. Thus we muſt do with <hi>our ſelves,</hi> nor is the Labour quite ſo perplext. Mankind is all <hi>Labyrinth,</hi> and <hi>Diſguiſe,</hi> and never ſhows the ſame Face two hours together. I know my ſelf better than all the Men in the World know me, and can be more juſt and faithful, according to Truth, in my Judgment and Cenſure. They ſet up a <hi>Rule,</hi> and try all Complexions and Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by <hi>That,</hi> wildly, unreaſonably, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainly. I daily find them miſerably out in their Conjectures of me, even thoſe who think they beſt know me. They may frame a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Air</hi> of my Humour, by a frequent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, but are wonderfully miſtaken in their Application, as to the Ends, Inducements, and Motives of moſt of my Actions.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:94860:58"/>
            <p>The moſt ſtupid <hi>Soul</hi> that is, will ſometimes <hi>work</hi> upon her ſelf, review her own Thoughts and Inclinations, and would delight to be more Converſant in this Exerciſe, if we did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt her Meditation by the Propoſal of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Objects, which do not at all concern her. It is the beſt Acquaintance we can have, and would deal more faithfully and wiſely in her Adviſements than the beſt Friend we know up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth. It is, I am confident, the want of this Intelligence that occaſions all the Irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities and Diſorders we are <hi>guilty</hi> of. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to make <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> of your <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and you will ſoon perceive your Anxiety, and Torment abated. Then ſhould we not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be <hi>Wiſe,</hi> but in a great meaſure <hi>Happy</hi> to boot: And for ought I know in as high a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree as humane Nature is capable of attaining. For the greateſt part of our <hi>Felicity,</hi> as I take it, in this Life, is placed in a due manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Afflictions, or the intire <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> and <hi>Monarchy</hi> of Reaſon over our <hi>Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> It is a prejudicate Opinion, begot by <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> fomented by <hi>Education,</hi> and inveterate by <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> which has infected our Minds and debauch'd our Palates, that we can reliſh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing according to it's true, and natural <hi>Taſte.</hi> For the Objects we converſe with, have for the moſt part an <hi>indifferent</hi> inclination to <hi>Good,</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> and operate upon us only after the Judgment we make of them. We are <hi>Maſters</hi> of every thing before us, and a <hi>wiſe</hi> Man hath an admirable <hi>Dexterity</hi> of drawing <hi>Sweetneſs</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:94860:58"/> from what <hi>others</hi> call a <hi>Calamity:</hi> And makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the Injuries of Fortune, ſerve his Deſigns, and further his Advancement. They are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erally Men of weak Spirits, who are deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h <hi>Adverſity,</hi> or exalted with <hi>Proſperity.</hi> And who is either way affected with theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings, gives a ſtrong Argument of his <hi>Imbeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> that he knows not how to live <hi>agreeable</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o either <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Will any Man Glory in another Man's Excellencies, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue himſelf, becauſe his Neighbour has a Houſe better furniſhed than his own? The Caſe is the ſame. Whatſoever is in the Power of <hi>Fortune,</hi> belongs not to us. We ought no more to be concern'd at her Contempts, than elevat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with her Favours. She is a capricious <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs,</hi> and the Frailty of Mankind is the ſubject of her Humour. She ſwells a <hi>Bubble</hi> with <hi>Pride,</hi> and breaks it with <hi>Scorn.</hi> Whoever truſts her, does but Treaſure up to himſelf an abundant, and <hi>inexplicable</hi> Matter of Diſcontent and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation.</p>
            <p>I could (in ſome fits of contemplative Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly,) fall aſleep as ſoon in a Church-Yard as on my Bed; and am often ſo weary of dull Life, that my greateſt delight is in ſuch <hi>Objects</hi> as ſpeak moſt to it's <hi>advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know that I carry <hi>a Ghoſt</hi> always about me, and that I my ſelf am <hi>a Walking Spirit.</hi> This thought allays in me thoſe vulgar <hi>Fears</hi> of the haunts and viſits of <hi>Spectres.</hi> And as I am not at all afraid of my ſelf, ſo I am very little ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of <hi>Apparitions:</hi> Nay more, I could
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:94860:59"/> wiſh the <hi>Communications</hi> more frequent betwix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>us</hi> and the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper World:</hi> I would harden our <hi>Chriſtian Courage,</hi> familiari<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to us the Thoughts of <hi>Separation;</hi> and creat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in us a more paſſionate love of the <hi>Heaven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pretend not by the <hi>Title</hi> of this ſmall Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe to any extraordinary <hi>Scheme</hi> or new <hi>draug<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of Religion for Men of my own Profeſſion much leſs would I be thought ſlighly to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt any neglect or deficiency of theirs in the Practice of the <hi>Old:</hi> I am very well aſſur'd, that <hi>Religio Bibliopolae</hi> ſeems a direct <hi>Tautologie</hi> But ſurely it can be no Offence to ſay, that I could wiſh we were all more in earneſt for <hi>Heaven,</hi> and that we had all the Wiſdome and Vertue that ever appeared in the <hi>guiſe</hi> of true Reaſon in the World, ſumm'd up and amaſſed in a <hi>Chriſtian Book-ſeller;</hi> eſpecially in a daily, ſincere contempt of this World.</p>
            <p>No eager purſuit, or reſtleſs intemperate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Wealth or Honour, muſt be harboured by us, who are to fix our whole hopes <hi>on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Country;</hi> and we ſhould confeſs our ſelves <hi>Strangers</hi> and <hi>Pilgrims</hi> on this Earth, by the Precepts and Examples of all the <hi>Holy Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> throughout the whole Book of God. To ſet any extraordinary <hi>value on the World,</hi> is to unravel the peculiar Principle of Chriſtianity, and <hi>run retrograde</hi> to the ſteps of the <hi>Holy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94860:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
